He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
...
Greetings, dragon slayers, demon veins, and gigantic eloks.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits,
podcast my co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in a Mayan's Pennsylvania.
This is a pre-recorded episode.
So we're not gonna be taking any live calls for this one.
But we do have some voice mails from you
that we're going to be including.
Well, now, if someone...
does through some kind of clairvoyant connection realize that we're recording it and call the
studio right now as we're recording.
I don't know what would happen.
And so what's there to pick it up?
There is a chance, right?
So I'm just going to put this vibe out into the universe.
So you're saying there's a chance you could make a live call right now.
It's it'd be the only one.
You're going to somehow become aware of what I'm saying.
So how long should we wait on that?
Oh, not wait. Okay. So yeah, well here in the United States, it's Thanksgiving. Or is the late Archbishop of
Arche, Diasis, Metropolitan Philip is said to have called it the only American holiday they haven't ruined yet.
So if you are one of our American listeners, I hope that it's truly a day of thanks for you and yours.
As many of you probably know, ruin it every year by losing.
I'm sorry about your words.
fired Eastern Michigan.
Eastern Michiganers. That's why I wouldn't have taken you as a sports ball fan, but you know I learned new things about you every day
Well, how could you be a fan of the Detroit Lions is what I'm saying. I anyway
so
As many of you listeners probably know the word
Eucharist which is from the Greek of Charristia it means
Thanksgiving and you can still hear it in the modern Greek of Charristot which simply means thank you. That's how they say thank you
And it's the Eucharist we're discussing on this Thanksgiving episode.
of Lord of Spirits.
This is the second installment in our series
on the Holy Mysteries of the Orthodox Church.
So next to baptism, no sacrament of Christianity
is probably more debated than the Eucharist.
But what are its ancient roots as witness to
in the Holy Scriptures?
Why is it so important for most Christians?
Is it a sacrifice or a meal?
How does it relate to the Jewish Passover Seder?
So this is some of what we're gonna be discussing.
So my first question for you, Father Stephen, is this,
Isn't it all just a symbol?
No. No. I mean, you could have also said yes. Well, every time someone says the phrase
just a symbol, right? I think Pazzo, wherever he is, gets triggered. So, yeah, I was
like, I was trying to work it, work that into an angel gains its wings thing, but it wasn't
working. The joke wasn't working out for me. No, it's the opposite. Somewhere he just snapped
depends on half right because he sensed it.
someone had he just knew that way. Yeah. So okay, well, if it's not just a symbol, then
where where do we begin? Where do we begin? Right. So well, we as usual go way back in time.
Is this a chetelhoic moment or? Well, not that far back. Okay, okay. But we don't always go that far
back, but you know, eventually we'll get to actually talking about the Eucharist.
So we have to start with sacrifice and priesthood as such.
Yeah, right.
Because these things have something to do with each other.
Right.
And we're not going all the way back because we already did an episode on priesthood as such.
Yeah.
So we're not going all the way back to Adam as we did in that episode.
episode.
We're just going to talk here about the beginnings of the Christian priesthood.
And I know to some of our listeners, we know who we're talking about, the idea of a Christian
priesthood is not an idea that they like.
Yeah, yeah.
There's the notion that priesthood is an Old Testament thing and now we don't have that
anymore.
Right.
So what is it?
It means to talk about a Christian priesthood.
Are we just saying that the priests you find in Orthodox churches today are just sort of
a direct continuation of the priesthood of the tabernacle on the Jerusalem temple?
Yeah, Aaron.
And all them.
Right.
The Levitical priesthood, the Aaronic priesthood.
Answered no.
You
And in parallel to what we talked about last time when we were talking about baptism and
the relationship between circumcision and baptism, it's also not just this sort of simple
thing where like, well, there was that old priesthood and now there's this new priesthood
that replaced it.
Right.
Yes, there's continuities and discontinuities as you are wants to say.
So there's a more complicated relationship.
and that relationship is actually very much parallel to what we said last time, but we will sort of further
elaborate on that. But the place we have to start is that again, the Christian priesthood,
the priesthood of the Christian Church is not the Levitical priesthood. They are not the same thing.
These are two different things.
But in a similar
way to the way that we talked about last time that St. Paul saw Gentile Christians as receiving
the benefits of Christ's circumcision through baptism. We understand the Christian priesthood,
This is based on heavers in particular as being a particular
participation in Christ's priesthood.
So the Christian priesthood is really Christ's priesthood,
which is participated in by human people who play a certain role within the Christian community.
Yes, there's not this sense that individual people have their own priesthood, like that they
they are priests in themselves.
Right.
Christ is the priest.
And this is reflected in a lot of little ways actually in Orthodox practice.
Okay.
Right.
So to give you one very everyday example, that priests are all very intimately familiar
with, but maybe other folks haven't noticed.
and the bishop is around.
Right, is around your parish.
The priest doesn't use his hand to bless anything.
Right, because he's just the stand-in.
Right, but it's not just because he's just the stand-in.
Right, it's not just because of that.
It's not just because of the bishop about Rengson, but it's because that blessing is Christ's
blessing.
Right, so it's already available through the bishop.
Right.
There's one blessing and...
Since it's Christ blessing, the highest rank
it could give Christ's blessing.
But there's no need for example,
for even though I've seen some people do this,
like go around and get five different blessings
for five different priests who are standing around in a room.
Right.
And, you know, which is just kind of an informal thing to do.
But like if you think about, for instance,
in actual divine services,
while you might, for instance, as
some Russian liturgical practices want to do.
Send out a couple of deacons both with sensors
to do that synchronized sensing thing.
There is not synchronized blessings given.
Like you don't have a couple of frees
or a couple of bush-ups all stay out there
and see peace be to all,
and with their hands all moving at the same time,
like that's not a thing.
Right, just one.
And in the Orthodox Church,
the hand position is actually based on a weird anagram.
If you do it properly, which I can't,
and then know them.
But it's actually based on Christ's name.
Right.
So to emphasize that it's Christ's blessing.
And this is part of what's going on with the Cuffs and Orthodox Vestments.
We're going to talk about Vestments more when we get to the ordination episode in this
series on sacraments.
But the Cuffs sort of isolating your hands because they're not the priests' hands while
he's serving.
So, this is indicated in these sort of practical ways.
But so, before we get to sort of our participation Christ priesthood, we need to talk a little more
about what Christ priesthood is, right?
Because we're talking about Christ priesthood, but Jesus of Nazareth was not a priest on
this earth in the sense of being part of the Levitical priesthood.
Yeah, you don't see him going
into the temple and putting sacrifices in all turn doing those things.
Right.
So he was not, he had not a lot to do with the sageses in fact.
At least not positive interactions.
So he was not a priest in that sense.
So with priesthood, every priesthood is constructed around a sacrifice.
Right.
That's what I preached.
is as someone who offers a sacrifice.
Right. And so, like, for example, in the episode where we talked about priesthood,
and we talked about, for example, the priesthood being taken away from the elders of the people
and given to the Levites after the Golden Calf. Right. What was taken away and given to the Levites
was the authority to offer sacrifices. Yeah. Right. And as we said then, I think we have this very
modern
that the priests of the Old Testament were like leading worship, right? Which, of course,
is not the case because they were in the tabernacle offering incense. The people didn't go in there.
I mean, not standing up there with a worship team and saying, okay, everybody's saying, right,
they were not invited in, right? Inside the tabernacle where they had a service, right, every week.
Now that worked.
So the job of the priest, the thing that the priest is designated for is to be the one who makes
these sacrifices and offers these offerings. What makes the high priest, the high priest is not just
that he's like the boss of everybody. It's that he is responsible for fulfilling the particular role
in the Holy of Holies on the Day of Atonement. Right. So it's they're designated for this task and
of that time.
ask revolves around the offering of a sacrifice.
So if we're going to talk about Christ's priesthood,
what we, and we want to understand it,
what we have to do is identify
what is the sacrifice that Christ offers.
Yeah.
Right.
And simply put, it's himself.
Yeah, he's not handing it,
putting anything else on the altar.
Yeah, his priesthood is about his voluntary self offering.
I'm sorry.
That's a new thing.
I mean, you don't get that in the old covenant.
It's all you sort of do.
I mean, not in the sense of you get priests putting themselves where you're in.
Right.
No, not literally.
Yeah, you don't have priests like setting themselves up fire, right?
It's a bird offering.
And I don't think there's even, I don't think there's even within that Levitical priesthood,
I don't recall any language in the Old Testament talking about those priests as offering themselves,
and a kind of analog...
a metaphorical way. No, I mean, there's there's offering themselves as servants, right? I mean, you
can get to that, right? But not in a sacrificial self offering sense for a priest, right? Right.
Yeah. Yeah. But there's something else. So, yeah, so he's not, he's not a priest in terms of,
of like the functional
of butchering an animal, right? Right. But he is a priest in making the offering, the offering is
himself, right? So he's the one who offers, the one who is offered at the same time. Right.
I did not make that up. Yes, that is almost an actual quote directly from the Divine
energy. But we find...
this not just right liturgically but this for example is one of the major themes of St. John's gospel
is that sort of nobody can kill Jesus. People keep trying to kill Jesus
but he just slips away, he walks through the crowd. Sometimes it just literally says that it
like wasn't his time yet, so they couldn't.
You know, and Christ himself says,
eventually no one takes my life from me, I lay it down and I can take it up again.
Yeah.
Right.
And so St. John is really emphasizing this sacrificial element and that it's a voluntary
self offering that he's not like an innocent victim, right?
But that he is offering himself actively.
And
As I alluded to, while there isn't precedent for a priest offering himself, there is precedent
once we get into the second temple period of when you come to Jewish martyrs, which is a thing.
I think a lot of people associate like martyrdom being this Christian phenomenon that starts with
Christianity. It's not.
right? There were Jewish martyrs before that. When you get to that phase, you start
seeing the beginning of this idea. Right? We talked last time about how, from a
Christian perspective, the things that we have in the old covenant are part of
how that, part of what that's doing, a big part of what that's doing is
preparing Israel and then Judah, Judea to receive the Messiah.
Yeah, so it's right beginning to
form them to be able to do this right to be able to receive and understand
Right who he is and what he's doing. Yeah, they'll have it so they'll have a framework in mind already that they can interpret what they're seeing through
Right, and so part of that and you find this in second Maccabees and fourth Maccabees
There's a fourth Maccabees everybody's favorite books of the Bible if they're even in your Bible
And fourth Macabees, that's a rare set of eyeballs there.
Who's canon is that in?
It's in sort of in a appendix in this, in this lvonic.
Yeah, okay.
Which that's an interesting idea.
What does it mean to be in a canonical?
Well, exactly.
But that's not what this episode is about.
It's kind of at the edge of the canon.
So, but somebody you'll write a book about that eventually.
Yes.
But second...
Maccabees is a little more common. Second Maccabees you'll find in Roman Catholic
Bibles in the Orthodox study Bible in you know Bibles produced in the UK that
have quote unquote the apocrypha in them. Yeah right. The Deuteronocles whatever
they're called. So that's a little more findable. And both second Maccabees and
Fourth Macabees are from different perspectives talking about the same group.
group of martyrs in these kings.
And so what happens is this is, first macabees is sort of the history of the macabee in
revolt in the beginning of the Hezmonean dynasty, sort of in history form.
So it looks like first through fourth kingdoms or first and second Samuel, first and second
kings.
It's that kind of chronicle style.
Right, so second Macabees.
then sort of zooms in, right, to tell sort of particular stories during that period.
Okay. And so the most popular and most major story in second macabies is about the macabrean
martyrs, right? Who, it's an elderly man, a mother and her seven sons, who fall victim to the
the persecution of...
the Jewish people by the so-you-kid monarchs.
Okay.
Who were trying to stamp out Judaism.
And in particular, what they were doing was threatening people with torture and death
if they weren't willing to violate the Torah,
and specifically to violate those parts of the Torah
that marked them out as Jewish.
Yeah, right.
So that separated a Jewish person from a Greek person.
Yeah, and one of the big things that it ends up
focusing on is eating pork or not.
Right, right.
And there's a little added layer to that
beyond just eating pork, right?
Because the pork they're trying to get them to eat
is not just like farm fresh bacon, right?
Wait, was it sacrificed to idols?
Yes.
Yeah, because so pretty much meat in a pagan context is always the
thing with the primary sacrificial animal. Yeah, in Greek circles.
That's where the pork that was in the meat market, et cetera, came from, right,
was from these these pagan temples. But either way, right? This is something
that a faithful Jewish person was not going to do.
Right.
And so...
people like the Maccabee admirers were willing to literally be tortured and die rather than violate the commandments of God.
Yeah.
And this is part of why we talked a little bit last time about the circumcision issue that St. Paul faced.
This is why the charges against St. Paul by his opponents were so serious in the Book of Acts.
Right, they were accusing him of telling Jewish people to
Violate commandments that people in their collective memory had literally died rather than violate right and he's now acting like they're not important from their perspective
Yeah, that's why there's this animosity and great repentance and
The final accusation against him in the book of acts actually is that he brought Greeks into the temple and it specifically Greeks
Right, so it's it's plagued into this too, right?
It's not Romans or Gentiles.
It's specific.
Greeks. Yeah, the people that had been murdering them, not that long before. Yeah. So this, this is very
much in the mind of people, in the mind of the Jewish people, the people of Judea in the first
century, in the background of what's going on in the Gospels and Acts. So when they were condemning
the Romans, they were comparing the Romans to the Seljuk Greeks. But what you
Find in second and fourth Macabees.
Fourth Macabees tells the same story,
but fourth Macabees is really kind of like wisdom literature.
So it's sort of reflecting on the virtues
of these martyrs and that kind of thing,
but it tells the same story.
And what you find in both of them is that when the time comes
for these people to give up their lives
and they offer sort of their final statements
and their final prayers to God before being killed,
that they use the language
of offering themselves as a sacrifice,
as an atoning sacrifice, as a sin offering,
on the behalf of the Jewish people,
on behalf of their people.
And so the idea of martyrdom
and the idea of this kind of self offering
the sacrifice is there.
Right, sort of in the in the background and continues to be right so when when you get to the book of Revelation the souls of the martyrs are under the altar in heaven.
Yeah.
Right so they're still that kind of connection with martyrdom so we of course see Christ's
voluntary self offering as the fulfillment the filling full of that idea.
Yeah, and you know, you see in the liturgical
text from martyrs in the Orthodox Church. This idea is repeated over and it's really a trope,
you know, liturgically, that that's what they do. They offer themselves as sacrifices.
Yes, yeah. Yeah. And our hemnogamy emphasizes, although sometimes in weird archaic English,
But emphasize is over and over against the voluntary
nature. Yes. I'm thinking of what him in particular. Right. Right. Like, yeah, there's one
that Christ took pleasure at ascending the crowd. It took pleasure in ascending the cross,
which makes us sound like he was like, yes, this is going to be so great. Yeah.
Like he was having a great time. Yeah. No, it just meant that he was happy to do it. He was,
you know, he was doing willing, willing. Yeah. He was willing. Yeah.
According to his good pleasure means according to his will.
Right.
as every Calvinist listener knows. And we must still have one or two, even though I've
off put all of them many times.
So, this idea that this is a voluntary thing that Christ does.
They're offering of himself, his life, everything to his father.
So...
This is right, Christ's priesthood.
And so if the Christian priesthood is going to be a,
is going to be a priesthood,
it has to be oriented around a sacrifice also.
Right?
And if it's a participation in Christ's priesthood,
then the sacrifice that's offered by the Christian priesthood,
has to be itself, the sacrifice has to be a participation in Christ's self offering.
Right. It's not just an imitation of Christ's offering, right? Because, again, the priesthood
is not something that people hold in them themselves. So it's not like a Christian priest
is someone who also sacrifices himself on the altar in any literal sense. Right. I mean,
metaphorically okay, but the one who is offered is Christ.
or does a separate, right, unrelated sacrifice.
Right.
Because it would be a different priesthood
than Christ priesthood.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
Because it would be centered on a different sacrifice.
And so this is our sort of first point here
about the Eucharist is that the Eucharist
is not this sort of independent ritual thing, right?
disconnected from Christ's.
sacrifice, Christ's voluntary self-offering. Right? So I think, for example, the book of Hebrews
makes this pretty clear. This is the whole idea of Christ as the high priest. Right? You don't have
a high priest with no priesthood. Yeah, right. It's like being God of God without any other gods,
or Lord of the Lord's. So, right? Like really doesn't make sense. So
So I think...
many, many folks, some of whom may be in our listening audience, make, make the mistake,
like when they understand that adhebrews, of assuming that the sacrifice that Hebrews talks
about, uh, Christ offering in the heavenly places, which is himself, right? They, they
they'd agree with us there. But the idea that that now sort of obviates and removes any
any kind of participation in any action.
sacrifice any other priesthood on earth, right? As if sort of... Well, it's really read this way.
It's read this way that Christ sort of abolished the sacrificial system by taking it up into heaven with them.
Yeah, it's sort of one and done that it's over now. He did what was needed. And I think that that stems
out of satisfaction theology, right? Well, God has now satisfied. So, well, that's done. Thanks.
Well yeah, well
Just about any atonement theory you can get that out of.
Right.
You really can't.
I mean, even like a Christus victor type thing, you could say, well, yeah, Christ won.
Yes, right.
He's victorious.
Done now.
Right.
Excuse me.
And that then breaks this connection.
So you have a high priest with no priesthood underneath.
Right.
have right no longer any
sacrifice and that would mean then that there's not a direct way for humans living in the world now
to participate in that sacrifice. It's now a historical and or heavenly thing with no material
connector except through, except in the past. And we'll get more into that in a little bit here.
in a second half actually.
Yeah.
But for now the point we're making is that the Eucharist as the sacrifice around which the Christian priesthood centers
participates in Christ
self-offering which is a single event, right?
Which is both an eternal heavenly event that Hebrews talks about and an event that happens on earth at a particular point in time
right in our in the realm of human experience
that the
the Eucharist participates in that just as the Christian priesthood participates in Christ's
priesthood, that those are linked, right, directly. Now that said, as we talked about in the priesthood
episode, within Christian communities priesthood and eldership, you could say, or the press bitter it,
right are reunited. Yeah, right, right. Right. So when as we just referred to again,
after the incident with the Golden Calf, the priesthood is taken away from the elders of the people,
right, the presbyters of the people in the Greek translation. And given to the Levites,
the elders of the people remain the elders of the people. Yeah, right. But they lose the priest at the
the offering of the sacrifices.
split out. Yeah. Right. And as we talked about, that gets re-unified, right, in Christ. So that
means the Christian priesthood, the priest, while his role as priest, focus centers around
the Eucharist, he also has the role of Presbyter in the community.
Right. And that's our primary title actually. Although priest is in English, is derived from that.
Yeah.
Yeah, right. It's a weird thing in English that both President and Priest derive from the
ancient Greek word, but as Vietroth's. But it is the case.
Right. So this elder role is still there. That's part of where the father title comes
from. Right. We talked about that more than that other episode.
So what more can we sort of say about Christ's priesthood?
Well, the...
elephant in the room on Christ's priesthood. The elephant in the room in terms of the entire
New Testament, standing in the background, and I know we've said this on the show before,
is Psalm 110 or 109 in the Greek, which is the most cited text in the New Testament.
Yeah, this is where we get that line. The Lord said to my Lord, sit out at my right hand until
I make the enemy as the footstooler that feed. Right, that's verse 1. Yeah. Right, that gets quoted a lot.
Right.
For familiar with the New Testament you probably think of examples, but the next verse is important too
Which is you are a priest forever according to the order of Melchizedek
And the you right the Lord right Yahweh the God of Israel is still the one talking
And he's still talking to the person who David calls my Lord and
And not just from the New Testament, but from other Second Temple literature we can tell that pretty much every-
understood that the my lord in Psalm 110 was the Messiah. So the Messiah is not only
lord but also a priest forever according to the order of Melchizedek. Right. And
and Melchizedek, CR Melchizedek episode, is was both the king and high priest of
Jerusalem. Right, right. So the order or the pattern, right.
the the mode of Melchizedak is referring to this that he is the Messiah by being the Messiah is the king right
And he's also a priest
right, he's also a high priest and
This is what Hebrews does in terms of Christ priesthood and his high priesthood right and
So the major disjunction between this kind of priesthood and the Levitical priesthood
As Hebrews points out, is not,
it being re-unified with kingship.
Right.
That's not the major disjunction.
I mean, that's true.
These were split with Moses and Aaron, as we've talked about.
And they're, right, recombined in Christ, as we've talked about.
But the major disjunction is that the priesthood of Melchizedek
not a hereditary priesthood.
Yeah, we don't see the sons of milk. I mean, like that's just we just see milk is it it because this there aren't any priest, right?
Yeah, this is why Hebrews talks about he doesn't have a father. He doesn't have a genealogy. He doesn't have it right yeah
So you look at chronicles
Right you'll get Ezra
These huge
Geologies of all the priests and Levites and the different groups who did different things in and around the temple right
He bruises point exactly.
but Kinseneck doesn't have a GDLG at all.
He sort of comes from nowhere, disappears to nowhere.
So this lack of a hereditary link is the major disjunction.
What does that mean?
How does this priesthood then get handed down?
This is why the concept of apostolic succession becomes so important.
right within the Orthodox Church.
Within the Christian Church in general, right?
It's because just like in the Old Covenant,
no one can take the title or role of priest upon themselves voluntarily.
No one's self-ordained.
Right, yeah, we don't get self-ordained people.
We don't have a guy just decide to go start a church
and make himself the pastor of the church.
This doesn't happen.
Well, it does happen. Those are called heretics.
In their literature.
Yeah, and I think it's also in some ways a kind of confusion of the role of priest and
prophet to, you know, prophets are called directly by God.
But it's interesting God doesn't call, doesn't do that with priests there's always a line,
you know.
Right, right.
And so this line is not hereditary.
This is what happens in some Greek villages.
Right.
I mean, you know.
There are fathers and sons who are priests. I actually know a priest who's like a 13th or 14th generation priest, which is amazing.
But that's not, it's not a given, you know.
Right, right.
But what we see is, right, Christ chooses his apostles.
Yeah.
His disciples and apostles. He makes them apostles by sending them out.
Right. And then they choose the deacons and acts. They choose
as they go out.
and form these Christian communities, they choose the next generation of
bishops, which we see with, for example St. Paul and St. Timothy, right? And then
that next generation of bishops chooses the next generation of
presbyters and deacons and then they consecrate the next generation of bishops
and so on and so on down to the present day. Yep. Yep. Right. And so you do have a
a line, you do have a tree.
a tree formed by the laying on of hands not by biological descent.
And it goes ultimately back to Christ, choosing the apostles.
But so that's how you have that kind of tree without it being hereditary, and also without
it being people irrigating titles to themselves.
We can't stop people from doing that, but we can not recognize it.
Yeah. Right?
You can call yourself the grand moofty if you want to, but I can't stop you.
But no one else will recognize that claim.
Are you seeing an ordination to the universal life church doesn't count?
Not according to the state of Pennsylvania if you want to marry somebody.
Oh really? I actually have never even looked in that.
That's pretty fun.
Yeah. So, yeah, for a stretch of the light of Elvis, I think they could only practice
in Vegas. So, all that said, right, we do have to spend at least a little bit of time on
this idea that the Eucharist even is a sacrifice.
Yeah, because this is a big point of contention, especially around the reformation.
Yes.
In the 16th century, this becomes a big deal.
Right.
Yep.
But, but, biblically, there's not really a way around this.
Yes.
There just isn't.
Yeah, it turns out that St. Paul explicitly makes this linkage.
Yeah.
So I had a journal or article on this, published by...
rule of faith that you can go look at online.
I'm not going to rehearse all that here,
especially the footnotes.
But if you're a fan of footnotes,
wait, wait, you're a footnotes?
That's a good one to go.
Yeah.
I was told that you don't.
I have more than 600 footnotes in my dissertation,
full of excitement.
Ooh, so.
But when we read 1 Corinthians 10
Verse 14 through 22, this is part of in 1 Corinthians St. Paul's discussion of the Eucharist.
1 Corinthians is the major place where he discusses the Eucharist.
And because this was written before the Gospels were written, this is actually the earliest
discussion of the Eucharist, right, as such, that we have in the New Testament in terms
of what it was written.
And so in chapter 10 verses 14 through 22, he's actually at this one.
So he segues back and forth between a couple of topics in this whole section of 1 Corinthians.
Those two main topics being, hey, don't eat food offered to idols, right?
Right.
And here's 18 reasons why on the one hand and then on the other hand, talking about the
Yeah, because this
things are linked.
You're either on team God or team demons.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
So first Corinthians chapter 10 verses 14 through 22.
Therefore my beloved flee from idolatry.
I speak as to sensible people.
Judge for yourselves what I say.
The cup of blessing that we bless is it not a participation in the blood of Christ.
The bread that we break is it not a participation in the body of Christ because there is one
One bread, we who are many are one body.
for we all partake of the one bread.
Consider the people of Israel are not those who eat the sacrifices, participants in the
altar.
What do I imply then that food offered to idols is anything or that an idol is anything?
No, I imply that what pagans sacrifice they offer to demons and not to God.
I do not want you to be participants with demons.
You cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons.
You cannot partake of the table of the Lord and the table of demons.
We provoke the Lord to jealousy.
Are we...
stronger than he little threat there at the end.
Yeah good luck. Yeah right. You ought to fight it out with God. Good luck. Yeah. Yeah.
Yes, especially the verse 18 there, right? Consider the people of Israel are not those who eat the
sacrifices, participants in the altar, which is not saying that same word. Right. It's
participation in the blood of Christ, participation in the body of Christ, partake.
of the one bread participants in the altar. It's the same word. It's Kenania and Greek.
Various forms, right? And the same thing with participants with demons later on, right? So
Saint Paul here very clearly what he's trying to describe sort of how the Eucharist works or what
what it does, right?
His immediate comparisons.
right to teach them because they what they don't know about is the Eucharist
they know about oh there's sacrifices that go on at the Temple of Jerusalem
they know about pagan sacrifices they live in Corinth for Pete's sake right
they know what goes on there right and so he's saying this works just like that
So, Paul is very clearly directly saying the Eucharist is a sacrifice.
Yep.
You like the sacrifice that happens on the altar at the temple in Jerusalem, which was
still an operation at this point, like the sacrifices to demons that go out in those pagan
temples, right?
In the same way, right?
The Eucharist is a sacrifice, and in the same sense, not in a metaphorical sense.
He's not making a metaphorical comparison.
a direct comparison.
And this is again the earliest written, the right thing about the Eucharist.
It's from that letter.
So there are a bunch of distinctions that have come up since the 16th century to try to
dissociate.
And the reason for the record that we're saying Reformation and that kind of thing is that this isn't a Protestant thing per se.
Right, because our Lutheran friends
have priests have an altar see the Eucharist as a sacrifice, right?
At least some
some
number of our Anglican friends
There's a lot of diversity in the Anglican community, and shall we say?
Yes.
Yep.
But at least there is at least a strong tradition there
of seeing things that way.
So this isn't just Protestantism.
This is really a particular thread of Protestantism
that really frankly kind of get started with John Calvin.
Yeah.
But since in the United States,
the United States is just Protestant.
The culture is deeply Protestant
and not just Protestant but Purin.
And so far as Puritan Calvinist, this is a very common thread in American even gelical
Protestantism, which is why I started out with my half joking question, isn't it just
a symbol?
Yeah, it doesn't just stand for something else.
Right.
And so to try to get away from the idea of sacrifice alter priesthood with the Eucharist,
Bye.
a number of distinctions that get made that are frankly not
distinctions you can make biblically.
Yeah, right.
Like they're not there in the Bible.
I mean, you can certainly make distinctions in speech
theologically, right?
But it's all scriptural, you know, if they're not there.
The question is possible.
The question is, is the distinction you're making?
with what's in the scripture even if it's not found in the scripture.
Right. Right. And so for example, you get, well, when when Christ institutes the Eucharist,
he says, as it's usually translated in English, not coincidentally, do this in remembrance of me.
See, he calls it a remembrance or a memorial. Yeah. Right. And so that's not a sacrifice. It's a memorial.
But as is my want, I refer to
for people to numbers 10, verse 10 in the Septuagint, where the same Greek word memorial
is used to refer to the sacrifices on the Feast of Trumpets.
So sacrifices are then by definition memorials.
There's not one thing as a sacrifice and another is a...
will help you to think about this.
Right.
The call of the memorial does not mean not a sacrifice.
Yeah, I mean, in fact, it may very well mean sacrifice.
Yeah, like, and so does you get all this language in there
of remembering someone before God.
That doesn't mean to stand before God and say,
yeah, I remember him, you know, or, you know,
or even like God, let me remind you about about brother Robert,
you know, in case you forgot.
Yeah, that's not what that is.
It's really about a sacrifice on behalf of someone else.
Yeah, you know an offering yeah
So you also get this distinction made
between an altar and a table
Hmm so a lot of churches, right, they don't want to call it an altar. They'll have a table where
however often they do
the Eucharist
We'll get to not wanting to call it the Eucharist here in a minute, but
They'll call it a table, right, instead of it all.
And the problem is this is literally the same word, right?
In most ancient languages, up to and including Latin,
R-I means both table and altar.
And you can just look back at 1 Corinthians 10,
14 through 22 that we just read.
Right? You cannot partake of the table of the Lord and the table of demons.
What's the table of demons? He's referring to.
to. We'll clearly a pagan altar. Right.
So he could switch back and forth between altar and table.
Yeah, that's right.
There's a table's doing it.
There's an altar to God and there's an altar to demons.
Don't worship for the wrong one.
And the altar to God can also be called the table of the Lord.
And the altar to demons could be called the table of demons.
Yeah, right.
So there's not a distinction there.
And, relatedly, you get, and we did our three-part thing on sacrifice
where we kind of took this apart.
but this distinction between a sacrifice and a meal.
Sacrifices were meals.
For the most part.
Right, that's what they are.
Yeah.
So again, that's a non-starter, right?
In terms of saying it's a meal not a sacrifice.
That literally would not make sense to any ancient person.
Yeah, it's like saying it's Thanksgiving dinner,
not a meal.
Yeah.
Right.
That's what I said.
That's a type of meal, right?
Yeah.
So yeah.
So these distinctions aren't really supportable, right?
And what caused them really?
things when you look at the
Protestant Reformation. There are a lot of things that make sense in the 16th
century. Yeah and as Orthodox Christians we can have a certain level of empathy
with. Right. So if you're in the 16th century and the Church of Rome has
as supposed writings of church fathers.
Right. And things like the donation of constant team, that are forgeries.
Right. But nobody's sure and nobody can prove what's real and what's a forgery from the church
fathers. And the Latin vulga has over time changed in various ways and Latin words have changed
their meanings in various ways, right?
That's all languages do.
Right.
And...
And Martin Luther comes along and says, hey, you know what?
We can't be sure about any of this stuff.
Right? How far back it goes.
The only thing we can be sure about is, hey, we've got this Greek New Testament
that we got from refugees from Constantinople.
And we've got the Hebrew Old Testament that we got from the local Jewish community.
Right? And we know that Rome hasn't messed with either of those.
Because they have an edX.
access to it, right, to mess with it. So that's the only thing we can trust, and we need
to base all of our theology on that. You can kind of understand that in the 16th century.
Sure. Yep. Right? But when we get to the 21st century, and we know which of those
documents are fake at which ones are, and we can look at the textual history of not only
the Latin Vulget, but of the Greek, of the Hebrew, right, and we have all this available
to us.
There's no reason for us to sort of be stuck
in the 16th century.
And not just say, hey, the 16th century got it right
for the 16th century, but they got it right for all time.
Right, there will never be a point in the future
where we're able to do any better than the 16th century.
Right, we will never be able to have a better
biblical translation than the 1611 King James.
Anyway.
Bye.
that no knowledge will ever surpass or move us past the sort of scholarly consensus
of the 17th century Reforms Galastics.
They nailed it.
Yeah, it's a kind of perfectly arbitrary thing to pick, you know, right.
So and when it comes getting narrowing back in on our topic, right, from those other examples,
you really find.
here is this kind of reactionary position against abuses that were going on in the mass
in the 16th century in the West.
Yeah, like the idea, for instance, you know, built upon that whole system of purgatory
and indulgences and merits and so forth, the idea that offering the mass can give a certain
number of indulgences to people in purgatory.
That was one of the things that was was the practice and was the understanding.
Right. And some of these sort of weird,
eucharistic miracles to emphasize trans-abstantiation where you have eucharistic
hosts turning into human flesh and why not turning it visibly and to taste it, everything,
turning into blood, or bleeding host.
or some of these kind of things.
Or, you know, any number of, right,
other sort of excesses, just the whole idea of the mass
as a repeated propititory sacrifice, right?
There are things there going on
that you can understand why you'd want to correct them
from an orthodox perspective, right?
And the counter-reformation corrected some of them, right?
You
That's within the Roman Church.
But this reactionary position was assumed, right?
So not only is this not a repeated propititory sacrifice, this isn't a sacrifice at all.
Yeah, right.
Right.
Insert, not only...
Make it a fact-winter comment.
Yeah, like the odd and odd and odd, right?
And so this reactionary position was assumed that
For the sake of debate, for the sake of working toward correction of abuses, right, you can
under someone taking a more extreme stance.
But again, that stance then being set in stone for all time doesn't make sense, right?
Still having that reactionary stance of the 21st century.
There are much older.
your statings of the Eucharist, much more biblical understandings of the Eucharist, right?
That are neither that reactionary position nor the abuse you were worried about.
Yeah.
Right?
Yeah. I mean, a lot of it is founded on this idea that they had discovered, they had rediscovered
the biblical Christianity.
You know?
And so when you believe that you found it again, then it makes sense then you're like,
okay, we're back.
You know, like this is it.
So when I get...
get it, you know, on the one hand I get it. But a lot of this stuff becomes untenable,
especially when so many of those reactions are based on the limited information simply
available at the time.
Yeah.
And speaking from personal experience as a kid, the warning sign of this that you might
still be holding to an old reactionary position is if part of your Christian identity as a
Protestant.
is being not Catholic, which is totally a thing still for a lot of.
A lot of.
That's a warning side because our identity is Christian should never be based on what
we're not.
It should be based positively on what and who we are and who we worship and who we follow.
Right?
And so it's always, I'm not just picking on Protestants here.
Like if you're a Roman Catholic
in part of your identity is that you're not Protestant.
That's equally problematic.
If you're an Orthodox listener
and part of your sense of yourself as an Orthodox Christian
is I'm not a Protestant.
That's also a problem.
Right.
Or not a Catholic.
Or not a whatever.
Yeah, or not a Roman Catholic or whatever, right.
You're in a reactionary position
and that's by definition not balanced and not healthy.
Yeah.
Yeah, right.
So.
Now that I've bashed everyone, I thank the Lord that I'm not like those other
thoughts who say that they're grateful they're not Protestant or Catholics.
I define myself entirely on not being Father Andrew, which is why it gals me so
much would people online think we're the same person. Right, I mean we covered
this in episode one. Like literally within the first five minutes of
I recall correctly.
So, yeah, so in terms of then the Eucharist as a sacrifice, we talked about how it's a participation
in Christ's sacrifice, but along with that, we see within the Eucharist a certain gathering
up of the regular Old Testament sacrifices.
Yeah, which has this whole system of different kinds of sacrifices for different
purposes and so forth.
CR episodes on sacrifices.
Yeah.
And also, read Father Jeremy Davis's excellent book, Welcome In Gifts.
There you go.
This may be one of the most referential episodes we've ever done for me today.
Yes.
All we're going to do is reference past episodes and future episodes.
That's right.
Just a big bibliography episode.
It's purely a transitional.
I
three to five hours. Now people are going to check the time stamp.
So two of these types of offerings are part of that participation in Christ's sacrifice.
So we have the regular cycle of sin offerings, sometimes translated guilt offerings.
which is for forgiving sins.
In the Old Testament.
And we need to be clear, right?
As we were in that episode, right?
There is no substitution,
let alone penal substitution going on in sin offerings.
Yeah, because if there were,
that would mean that God is taking out his wrath on wheat cakes.
Yeah.
instead of on you.
Right.
Which so often it was weakaches and no animal died in the making of the sacrifice.
Yeah, yeah, that's the problem is if you're going to equal, you know,
make it about sub-pino substitution and that it's a death of an animal,
then that means you need to have an animal dying every time which you don't.
And it also means that the killing should be ritualized because it's such,
if it's the critical part, then there should be a ritual killing.
It's kind of just like, like, make sure you take it out of the
package kind of thing, you know.
Right, right.
You're not going to eat it without killing it.
Yeah, yeah, first.
But also, and this is important
for the penal part of the penal substitution,
the penal part involves suffering.
Right.
And the animals were never made to suffer.
Yeah, there's not a ritual beating this
proximal or strangling it or blinding it or
Um, but so
So this element, this is something we see in Christ's voluntary self-offering, and so
the Eucharist is a participation in that.
The next one is also, to give him a Christ's offering.
That's what's called the peace offering.
And those are, we talk about these much more in those previous episodes, but this is
a sacrifice that's offered after a strangement.
So humans have become estranged from God.
God and they make this offering and eat this meal to restore a peaceful relationship.
Yeah.
Let's get together and reconcile.
Right.
And this is not an offering that represents the end of God being mad at them.
Because God does not have things they did.
God does not lose it.
Right.
This is the end of their rebellion.
Yeah.
Right.
This is your kid.
It is done a bunch of stuff that's been ticking you off all day and they kind of feel bad
about it.
And so they draw you a picture and come and present it to you with a big smile as an offering.
Right.
You are not going to like kill your kid if he didn't do that, right?
But it is good.
Although you might say that.
Well, you know, I don't personally have kids, so...
maybe you guys do fly a DeMertors Rage as a couple of rats.
But I have not killed any of my children.
And I...
Yes, yes.
No.
The threat has to always be there.
So, and then the other major category of offering,
and this is the category into which the Eucharist
itself falls, like Eucharist.
as such, literally true.
as opposed to by participation.
Eucharist literally is a thank offering.
That's why it's called the Eucharist.
Right. As we started off, that's what the name means.
Right.
And within thank offerings,
in the Old Testament, the two basic ones are
grain offerings and drink offerings.
How about that?
You could kind of see how that works.
Right? How that fits.
Right.
And this is why, especially in the past,
while still with the bread today,
often in Orthodox churches,
but in the past with the bread and the wine
and even the water that was used,
those were brought to the church by people.
Often bread still is in Orthodox churches,
but it was all those things were brought every time
by the people.
as an offering to use in the Eucharist.
So as we said, Christ's self-offering sort of fulfills full,
right, is the ultimate example of all of these sacrifices.
The Eucharist participates in it.
And through the Eucharist, we then participate in it.
And this is why we've used the phrase before that of the Eucharist we come to.
and we offer bread and wine that we've brought. We offer this thank offering, this grain offering,
and drink offering, and we receive Christ in return. Christ not only offers himself to the Father,
but he offers himself to us, which brings us peace and reconciliation and brings to us.
the remission of sins. Yeah, it's all brought together in Christ in every
direction. I mean, that's just fast. That's really it's it's a little mind-bending
right that he's the offer and the offering the one. I can't remember the
exact line now from the liturgy. You know that he's the one. The offer the offering
the acceptor or recipient. Yeah, yeah. He received.
He gives the offering, he gives the offering, he is the offering, he's the one being distributed.
Right. Yeah. Everything is Christ within this context.
All right, well that's our first half. We're going to go ahead and take a short break and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young will be back in a moment to take your calls on the second half of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237.
2, 3, 4, 6.
That's 855 AF radio.
Introducing a new book from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Healing work.
Giving humanity a second chance.
Written by Joshua McCool.
Healing work is essentially a how-to guide
to help readers locate the starting point
in their own healing process
and gain confidence.
and responding to the ebbs and flows, successes and setbacks of the healing journey.
This book is about helping people learn how to make their healing journey shorter.
It's tragic that so many get stuck in distressing emotional patterns for years or even decades.
Often because they simply don't know how to identify why they're suffering.
We can work to reduce unnecessary emotional suffering by learning to identify what we need to focus on
and by developing skills to navigate the emotional...
between the extremes of anger and happiness.
Healing work, giving humanity a second chance.
Available now at store.AncientFace.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 858 F
Radio.
Welcome to the second half of the show.
Thank you very much, Voices and Steam.
But this is not a live show.
This is a pre-recorded episode.
But we do have some calls that we received, some voicemails.
And we're going to make use of those starting in this part of the show.
So unless our vibes have reached you, I do somehow know to call in as we're recording.
Yeah.
This is where we get accused of being new-agers.
I'm told vibes is a new-age word, I don't know.
Is it?
I'm from Southern California, so it's hard to discern.
Everything's vibes there?
Yeah.
Actual vibrations.
Dude, quit harsh in my mellow.
I remember the Beach Boys song Good Vibrations, which suggests that there are evil vibrations.
Oh, there are bad vibes, dude.
I walked into that one.
Yeah, so all right, well we're talking on this Thanksgiving episode, we're talking about
the Holy Eucharist and we discussed the question of sacrifice and the priesthood in our first
half and now we're going to continue talking about the Eucharist and continue of course
talking about the Old Testament and how all these things kind of are related to each other.
So let's roll.
Let's talk about the Passover. That's related, right?
Transform and roll up.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, right, so we talked in the first half,
we were talking about the relationship
between the Eucharist as sacrifice and the priesthood
and the sacrifices of the old covenant.
and so this half
The second half, we want to talk about the relationship, the special relationship the
Eucharist has with the Passover directly.
Because in addition to sort of as we mentioned taking up all of those earlier sacrifices, being
a participation in Christ's sacrifice, which itself is the fulfillment of those things
in being the fullness.
of the patterns established there.
There's a directed special connection to the eating of the Passover,
which is Hosca being the Greek word for Passover.
So we'll probably use those interchangeably.
Yeah, I mean, in Greek they literally are just interchangeable.
Right. It's the Greek word for Passover.
Yeah. And it's also what we call what the Germanic people's call Easter.
Hahahaha
I don't even know if it's all of them. I'd have to check, but it's true. It's a specifically Germanic language term
Yes, sorry in Germanic language. Yeah, sorry everyone who somehow thinks that a Christian feast that arose in the ancient near East
Just somehow named after a Germanic goddess
Nothing we're no it's Ishtar is ishtar
The Germans just remembered they should Babylonian.
Yeah, right.
Yeah, yeah.
Easter has as much to do.
Easter as a holiday has as much to do with Ishtar
as celebrating the Fourth of July means
that we're giving worship to the divine genius
of Julius Caesar.
Well, I don't know what you do on the Fourth of July.
Yeah.
Yes.
Right.
That is right.
So yeah.
Yeah, the correct response to Eddie would tell you
that Easter or
Pascas, a pagan holiday is to ask them if they consider Jewish people to be pagans.
Because it's literally Passover. But so Passover, we, of course,
often in the Orthodox Church, were referred to Pascas as the Feast of Feasts. We're celebrating
Christ's resurrection, kind of obvious why that would be the Feast of Feasts. But that's also true
in the Old Testament.
Right, right that Passover the Passover is the Feast of Feast in that
Festival cycle as well. Yeah, the highest of all high holy days
right and so
in
The Old Testament it is it represents the beginning of
One of the Festival cycles right so when
and the instructions are being given by God to Moses about.
the celebration of the Passover, he says, this will be for you the first of months.
Right.
Which you like, wait a minute.
I thought that the feast of trumpets was the first of months.
Yeah.
What happened to Russia, right?
Right.
Uh, that's, um, and that's because, um, and I'm pretty sure we've talked about this
before on the show.
Yeah.
But, um, there were two different overlapping calendars and festival cycles, right?
in the calendar as a
it's laid out in the Torah.
You have the older actually calendar
that's based on the agricultural cycle.
Right.
And that's where you get the early September
beginning of the year.
And then you have the festival cycle
that's based around Passover.
Right.
And this is still true in the Orthodox Church calendar, right?
We have a set of feasts that are based around.
Posca.
every year. And then we also have the addiction on September 1st, the beginning of the ecclesiastical
year. We have the cycle of fixed date feasts.
Yeah, and this is what keeps all those people who are up to interpret the, interpret the
tipicon for us in business. Yeah.
It creates this beautiful complexity. Right. But that's a, that's a point of continuity.
Right. I think that we still have these two, these two layers.
Yep.
Um, so...
But the cycle centered around PASCA is sort of the most important.
That's why it overlaps and sort of trumps the other.
Right? Right? Right?
And it moves around in relation to the other.
So another interesting thing that we've noted before
is that the future observance, right?
how the Passover will be celebrated and observed.
annually in the future is actually presented by God to Moses in Exodus before the Passover event actually happens.
Yeah, and before the 10th plague.
Right, and it's worth noting, especially that this feast and then all the other feasts related to it are,
they're not about sort of natural cycles, right, like that other calendar.
These are God acting in history.
Right.
Right. That's why I get the prompts. Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
That's underlying then by like, okay, I'm about to do this.
And this is how you're going to celebrate it.
Right.
It's based on this act and it's right before.
Right?
So key to, this is key to the way the Torah presents.
The Passover is that it's not presenting the Passover as a single one-time historical
event that will be reflected on later.
It presents the Passover as the beginning of an ongoing reality.
That's the pattern that will continue into the future without an endpoint.
And so that makes that one sense of memorial, I said we'd return to this, that makes
that one sense of memorial of just remembering a past event impossible.
Yeah, right. Because...
That's not where it's focused.
We see the same thing with the Eucharist that Christ describes how the Eucharist will
be celebrated.
It says, this is my body broken for you before his body had been broken.
This is my blood shed for you before his blood had...
been shed. Right. There's a participation even before the event in terms of historical
linear time. Right. And so he's instituting this before the event happens to convey the
same thing. Right. Not just to parallel because he's doing this at Passover. Yeah. This
is the new Passover, right? The renewed Passover. Right. He's doing it at Passover. And he's
not just presenting this as his death and his resurrection are going to be this historical
event that will someday be in the distant past and we will reflect and look back at.
Right. Because that wasn't even possible. You know, because he's not like, well, I remember when
tomorrow. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And this is, so this is an ongoing, he's creating again. It's not just
the singular mighty act of God in history, but it is this reality that will continue with no
So stated endpoint, right?
other than the return of Christ, the end of the world.
Right?
Yeah.
And that's the language of as often as you do this, you'll proclaim his death and his
resurrection until he comes.
Right?
So it is this ongoing thing.
And the fact that this temporal relationship between when Christ institutes the Eucharist
And when he...
actually dies and rises again, right? Is re-interrated in our
liturgy in our Orthodox liturgy? Yeah, right. Where, say, there's that line,
and it's only in Christostom's iteration of liturgy. I don't think this is in Bezos.
He says, on the nightingh which was betrayed or rather, gave himself up for the life of the world.
Yeah, so it's being directly connected.
We have the gave himself right so we have the voluntary self offering element there.
Right.
We have the Eucharist as a participation in that but we also have a reminder that this
is instituted right before he does it.
Yeah, and there's both this kind of historical earthly expression on the nighting which is betrayed.
And then here's the you know the inner reality that maybe is not a true looking.
You know what really happened is he...
yourself up for the life of the world, you know, and both things are true.
How, how?
How, how, how, how, how, how, how?
So, um, and so another element that we see in the Passover, right, and its celebration
is that the the Passover
involves the whole family.
Yeah, yeah.
So related to that.
Has it sort of led by the father in his sort of priestly role.
But it encompasses the whole family.
Yep.
So related to that, we have one of our first voicemails
that I'm going to play for everybody.
And we'll talk about it.
Hi, father Andrew and father Stephen.
My question about the Eucharist relates
to the fact that in orthodoxy, we give the Eucharist
to infants in the private-
tradition that I grew up in that was not the case. One typically received
Holy Communion the first time at the age of 13 or 14 and only after
passing the material and a catechism or confirmation class to the satisfaction of
the pastor and when I explored Orthodoxy the fact that communion was given even
to infants was something that was very attractive to me as I explored the
church. Could you explain some of the rationale behind why this
has always been the practice in the church, is it related to any notions of the sacrifice
of Christ and the Eucharist, a sacrifice, an effect that infants who have been born again
by water in the spirit also need to be nourished with the life-giving body and blood of Christ
that sustains our faith and helps us to grow in our faith.
Yeah, so that comes to us from Yonkovos, he didn't introduce himself, but that was on
email so thank you very much for that that question.
and Yakovah. I mean, this is directly what we're talking about here, right? There's in the
Passover celebration, the whole family is involved. There's no indication that you have to be a certain
age, that you have to pass classes or anything like that. Right. And the children are not only
like included, but the one little bit of actual Passover liturgy that's in the Hebrew Bible
itself right is
this sort of mini dialogue between father and son.
Right. So the children have a particular role because part of
what's going on in the Passover meal is that this is
intergenerational. Right. It's handed down. Right. Yeah. So,
Yeah, there's there are
some, not a lot. There are some Protestant groups. There are some Presbyterian groups who
practice what they call Pado Communion, which I think people are going to have to get rid
of terms like Pado Communion and Pado Baptism, because I think they're going to be like really
unpopular soon, because they have other connotations.
Yeah, but it just means communion for kids baptism for kids.
Yes.
That's good.
Yeah.
But that's a definite minority.
Right, it process.
And of course, Roman Catholicism doesn't
commune infants normally.
Right, right.
I mean, the 1.5% of Catholics who are Eastern Catholics do.
And historically, I can't remember exactly when it was,
but historically Latin Catholics would commune infants,
but it's not been for many centuries.
that they did. Yeah, it's not common practice anymore. So yeah, I mean, there's always
a temptation to punt and say, well, hey, you have to explain to me why not. But we have,
we have available to us various groups, explanations, why not? And we can interact with those,
So one of them is actually kind of confusing to me.
That's not being totally genuine.
One of them doesn't make sense to me.
I'm not really confused.
I just think it doesn't make sense.
So, and that is there are some of our Protestant friends
who are very anti-sacrimental,
meaning they're against the idea of sacraments.
Yeah, right, sure.
They don't like the word, right?
They won't use the word.
I know of Protestant pastors who have literally
What do you?
a baptism or something or or or or serve communion, it give a talk before
I had explaining how it's not a sacrament. Oh, right. Exactly. I mean, I remember in my
in my even to local days, especially, especially in baptisms, you would get a
little mini sermon saying that this doesn't do anything. Right. And so here's my
thing where I don't understand or to be more honest and less nice. I don't think
make sense.
is a lot of these same people who have the position that it doesn't do anything
won't do it to infants. Yeah, baptism doesn't do anything contradiction. It's just
a symbol but I will not apply this empty symbol to anyone under a certain age.
Right? Or right, communion is just symbolic. We're just remembering Christ.
what he did for us, but you have to be a certain age.
That is what makes sense to me, right?
The version of that that makes more sense to me,
I still think it's incorrect,
but that I understand the argument is groups that,
believe it does something, right?
That it is, right?
In the tears of the Eucharist.
Yeah.
And think that in order to receive the Eucharist
worthily, in order to participate in it in a worthy manner,
you have to have some level of intellectual understanding
of what it is and what's going on.
Yeah.
Right.
That they say an infant doesn't have.
And that's why there's an age thing.
Right.
You have to reach your certain age and have
a certain understanding.
There's a bunch of problems with that.
One of them is, right, maybe this is just me being orthodox and mysterious, right?
But is there someone out there who really understands the Eucharist?
Right.
So, we all have these partial understandings, right?
And, you know, but it has to reach a certain level of partial, right?
Before.
Yeah.
I mean, the version of this that makes the least sense to me is, um,
with folks who have,
honestly, it's hard for me to keep track
of what the proper term is now,
but intellectual disability or however you want to describe it,
forgive me if that's offensive to anybody.
Especially if they're profoundly that way,
like say, for instance, they'll never be able to speak
and it's clear that they don't have much mental understanding.
On that basis, you would have to,
for their whole life, refuse them to commune.
And I end and you know, for.
those who believe who apply the same rule to baptism that they would go their whole life
without being baptized. Now, if you are in a purely memorialist tradition, then you
probably would say, well, it doesn't really matter, you know, one way or the other,
then because it doesn't do anything. So it doesn't matter if you do it or not. But that's
the one that doesn't make any sense to me is, is, yeah, for people whose understanding
never will reach that level. At least as far as we can tell.
I used to use that as an example and unfortunately I found out recently that there are a lot
of Roman Catholic priests who will not give the Eucharist to someone who is mentally disabled.
Right. Yes. There are people, yes, and there are Protestants who will simply say, yeah, no,
they would never because they have to be able to make a confession of faith.
I know we have some Roman cap.
I'm not trying to be anti-catholic.
No.
But I have to be honest and say, and I now live in a majority Roman Catholic era.
And there's a lot of very bad pastoral praxis that goes on.
That I think is one of them.
I think infants should receive the Eucharist.
Okay.
But if your practice is not to give inference to your curious, that isn't like make me upset.
Right?
But when you tell me that someone has a traumatic brain injury and so now you will never allow them to share in the body of blood of Christ again, that does get me upset.
No.
When you tell me that because somebody's dad got divorced and remarried you won't baptize them.
That gets me upset. So this is not just me taking shots at the Roman Catholic Church
Willie Nilly, but I think that is. I mean like I can't understand how a
compassionate human being could do that. And so props to and I'm definitely not
going to name them and get them in trouble. Props to the Roman Catholic priest who
I know of who bypassed those rules for the sake of compassion.
Right. Kudos to you for disobeying your high rarks. You think you'd hear that on
ancient faith. Well, I mean, you're telling Catholic priests that it's good to disobey
their higher. Yeah, I'm telling Catholic priests it's okay to disobey the Pope. So there we go.
Yeah, right. Can't get in trouble for that where I live. I'm into disobeying the Pope as well.
Yeah, yeah, so yeah, so to me, right, the
the core is, the core is the reality of human life. Right? First and greatest
commandment, love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, with
all your mind, and with all your strength. Okay? At the beginning of our life, our
mind and our strength, they're not really there yet. We still got our heart and
our soul, with which to love God. Right? And none of us remembers what our
relationship with God was like.
like in the womb, for example.
But it's totally wrong to assume that there wasn't one.
All right.
And then when we get to the end of our lives,
our mind and our strength start to go.
Yeah.
But we still have our heart and our soul
with which to love God.
And so the idea that we are going to exclude people
from the family of God.
God from participating in Christ's self offering, the idea that we need to do that based on how much mind or how much strength they have doesn't make a whole whole lot of sense.
Yep.
spiritually or biblically. If you aren't loving God with your heart and your soul, then
we need to talk about you not receiving the Eucharist. But if you're loving God with
everything you've got...
It doesn't matter how much or how little you've got.
Yeah.
Yep.
So, another one of the big objections, of course.
We mentioned this earlier is the idea that the Eucharist is a repetition of Christ's crucifixion.
He's being re-sacrified and so forth.
But that doesn't work based on what we already said, right?
This is a participation in an event that has occurred.
it's not a repetition of that event, right?
So is another continuity with Passover?
Yeah, right, exactly.
So in the Passover, it's not, and now tonight,
we're gonna remember when our ancient ancestors
were saved from Egypt.
It's this is the night that we were brought out of Egypt.
And I mean, this gets repeated.
I mean, God uses this language when he's speaking to Israel.
I'm the Lord who brought you up out of Egypt.
And you might be talking to people who are generations removed
from those who actually made the Exodus.
So it's again, you are brought out of Egypt.
And so when Christ offers himself, we are saved.
It's not, oh, let's remember when those people were saved
2,000 years ago, we're participating in that offering
of Christ as it happens.
It's kind of you are there.
So it's not a repetition.
It's a return in a sense.
But it's not a repetition.
Repetition would be, if once a year,
all the Jewish people.
the world flew to Egypt and then made an overland trek.
Yeah.
Right.
Where's Yom Suf again?
Right here on this map.
So that's not, right?
Reenactment.
Yeah.
That's not how any of this works, right?
They're participating in the event that happened, right?
In the past.
They are not repeating it.
It's a ritual, it's a ritual, it's a ritual.
Yes, yes, yes, not a repetition. That's the difference. Yep. Yep.
And as we've mentioned before,
but when these commandments are being given, right,
what God says he's going to do through the Passover event
is make a distinction between the Israelite and the Egyptian.
Hmm, so the previous plagues...
for the most part affected the parts of Egypt where Israel wasn't living outside of the land
of Goshen. And didn't affect where Israel was dwelling. So if you were an Egyptian who happened
to live in an Israelite neighborhood, you just lucked out. And when missed most of the plagues,
right? But what happens with the 10th flag, with the Passover, God says he's going to make this
distinction.
He's going to draw the limit.
And so on that night everyone who participated in the Passover, ate the Passover, marked
their door, they're now Israel.
And anyone who didn't is now in Egyptian.
He's made this new nation for himself.
Right.
And so this is why you get the centrality of eating the Passover in the Israelite and
then, uh, Judah-I Jewish.
Right, identity, right.
And as we've talked about, that's why you find a canon,
always dangerous to talk about the minimums
because somebody's gonna be tempted to do it.
But you find the bare minimum in the cadets
of the church of being baptized
and receiving the Eucharist once a year at Pascha.
Right, at Passover.
Which parallels Israel, you've gotta be circumcised
and you've gotta eat the Passover.
Right, and if you don't...
Right then you become a lapsed Christian
It's now maybe an ethnic identity or something, but you're you're not observant your lapsed right
So
All that about sort of these things connecting
the the Eucharist and the Passover, but of course we
We don't just have the Eucharist once a year.
Right.
Well, we don't celebrate it just once a year.
Some folks may only receive the Eucharist once a year, but we don't just offer it once
a year.
Yeah, so this is only the things that's different from the Passover in the old covenant.
A point of discontinuity.
Yeah.
As a twer.
Well, because as we talked, in part, because as we talked about the Eucharist is taking
up that regular cycle of sacrifices also.
Yeah.
It's pulling it all in.
But sort of the minimal level, we have every Sunday,
right, the divine liturgy, the celebration of the Eucharist,
right, and that's because we not only have this annual cycle
with the annual commemoration of Christ's resurrection,
but every Lord's Day for us, right,
is the commemoration of Christ's resurrection.
Right.
Pasca continues.
And so we continue to offer it there.
And as we just mentioned, right, places and times, right, monasteries now, certain play,
other places and other times in the Church's history where you have daily Eucharist.
That's based on this, you know, that daily cycle of sacrifices there, sort of taken up into it.
Yep, right.
So this raises the...
the question about the relationship between the Eucharist and the Passover Seder as such.
Yeah. Is it just a Seder? Right. Or is it derived from the Seder? Some people say that.
And then also you get some, particularly some evangelical Christians, they will do
both a communion ritual and they will sometimes also hold
saders maybe invite the local rabbi or do it themselves you know the answer is no right it's to all of
that yeah it's not it's no not a sader right nope don't do that and we'll and we'll mention why
there seem to be some similarities between the two and just yeah because you know it's like it's not
there's nothing similar between the two but we'll talk about why right right it's so right off the
the bat.
In terms of whether the mystical supper or the last supper, the meal at which Christ
instituted the Eucharist, wasn't a satyr, it's the wrong day of the week.
So say, John's gospel especially makes explicit that Christ died at the time they were killing
the lambs.
Yeah, and to do a SATER you have to have a lamp.
already ready to go. Right. So yeah, doesn't match up. Right. So that said, right, that said,
what, what meal is this then? Yeah. What kind of meal is this? Because you know, Christ
and pass those, get this.
room, right, gives them a sign in everything, right? If here's how you find the room, you
get this room, we're going to eat the Passover together, right? Well, this is a kind of
meal which is described in the book of Deuteronomy.
Yes, not one of the ones that people seem to know. It's not quite as famous, but it's
It's related to all of this, right?
So yeah, it did around to me chapter 14,
verses 20 time.
through 26, you get this commandment from God.
You shall tithe all the yield of your seed
that comes from the field year by year.
And before the Lord your God,
in the place that He will choose to make His name dwell there,
you shall eat the tithe of your grain,
of your wine, and of your oil,
and the firstborn of your herd and flock
that you may learn to fear the Lord your God always.
And if the way is too long for you
so that you are not able to carry the tithe,
When the Lord your God blesses you because the place
is too far from you which the Lord your God chooses to set his name there, then you shall
turn it into money and bind up the money in your hand and go to the place that the Lord
your God chooses.
And spend the money for whatever you desire, oxen or sheep or wine or strong drink, whatever
your appetite craves, and you shall eat there before the Lord your God and rejoice you
and your household.
Right.
So this is talking about the annual pilgrimage to Jerusalem.
Hmm.
Right. Yeah, I'm noting where it says the place of the Lord your God chooses, which literally that's what happens right there
You know and right it makes his name dwell there in the temple, right? Yeah
And so this is also for the record Deuteronomy 14 verse 26 mark this down
This is the place where God tells you to buy liquor
Yeah, because it just speaks to the seeks between wine and strong drink
Yes, why?
or strong drink.
Or strong drink.
Or so you're not telling me the wines grape juice.
It's not that strong.
Some really strong welches tonight, honey.
This is fermented drink.
So sorry to our Baptist listeners, but this is in the Bible.
That's true.
So this is the kind of meal they're having.
We made our pilgrimage, right, and we're going to eat drink before the Lord.
Right, this is kind of reference a little bit sub-rosa in the tax like where Christ says he will not drink of
The fruit of the vine again until he comes in his kingdom
Right that this is sort of a celebratory type of meal now it doesn't turn out celebratory because Christ
Announces his betrayal. Yeah, kind of a kind of a dark turn at the end Judas. Yeah, looking at you Judas. Yeah
But it was attended to be
So
One of the things with the, so that said if it isn't a satir, right, if you've been to
one of these presentations or read an article written by somebody, and this is very common,
as Father Andrew said in the evangelical world now, drawing all these connections between
the Eucharist and the Passover satir, including things that are said, right, and that kind
That's it.
Yeah, specific ritual connections.
Yeah, yeah.
So, here's an audio footnote.
A good place to learn more about this history is Yuval Israel,
who's a Jewish scholar who's written a lot about this.
There's some lectures he's given that are on YouTube.
He says
provocative things like Christianity,
preceded Judaism.
That's half click baited.
I mean, he's pointing at something real,
but that's being click baited by him.
But one of the things he points out relevant
to what we're talking about here
is that actually a lot of the practices
within the satyr as it's now often celebrated.
actually went the other way. It's not that the Christian practice is based on the
Seder. It's that what's in the Seder is a sort of response to the Christian
practice. Yeah because if you look at what the Scriptures actually say about how
to do this meal, it doesn't include some of the stuff that gets pointed to as
being the links between the Seder and the Eucharist. Right, right. There's actually
very little. Yeah.
of actual ritual liturgics for the meal in the Torah, for example. So the specifics have sort of
no later. But so one example that Israel gives is the practice of lifting the unleavened bread
and saying something on the order of this is the bread of our suffering. Right. And people say,
Oh, look. See.
Christ lifted the bread and said,
this is my body broken for you.
Like suffering.
It actually went the other way.
Yeah.
Right. It actually went the other way.
Influence of Christianity on Judaism.
Right.
Or at least Judaism in part defining itself
over against Christianity.
Right.
So it's about the suffering of the nation of Israel
in Egypt and later rather.
than about the suffering of Jesus, right?
For example, right here.
So yeah, so ironically, right?
A lot of the Christian, quote unquote, Christian things
people are seeing in this aiter
are actually responses to Christianity,
not the origins of Christian practice.
Their responses to Christian practice.
So, as I just mentioned, and an obvious point of discontinuity, if you're familiar
with orthodox practice at least, is that when we celebrate the Eucharist, we use leavenbread.
Yeah.
Risenbread.
And Passover is very deliberately unleavened bread.
And this is because, right, this is a reflection.
for us. It is just being the correct way to do it. This is a reflection for us of the fact
that of Christ's resurrection. Yeah, risen bread for the risen Christ. Right. And that's
not just being punny. Right. But the idea is that we're not just, right. We're not just
focusing in the
Eucharist on Christ suffering, right, or just on his death, right?
But on his resurrection as well.
Yeah.
And his resurrection is celebratory.
Right.
The unleavened bread is the bread of suffering.
You make unleavened bread because you're about to go on the run from the Egyptians.
Yeah, you need something that's not going to go bad.
Yeah.
And you don't have time to let anything rise.
Alright.
You've got to get going.
Right.
So the Eucharist is not a participation in Jesus' last satir as we just said.
So that's why it's not on his resurrection.
Right.
Exactly.
And that resurrection element of the Eucharist is absolutely key.
Yeah.
Absolutely key.
Because his resurrection is what changes the Passover into what it becomes in Christian practice.
Right.
All right.
And so now to briefly grind an old axe of mine.
It's got to be pretty sharp by now.
Because once again, a good, respectable and decent Protestant pastor has expressed disbelief
that I do not see any sense of substitution in the Passover.
I will very briefly
reiterate why there is no substitution, let alone penal substitution in the Passover
ritual. And therefore, that also has nothing to do with the Eucharist. And so I'll try to
do this relatively quickly because this is not the first time I've done it, even on
the show, but notice there is no one to one correlation between lambs and sons.
So if you have a family, if you were in Israelite and you only had daughters, you still did the Passover.
You still follow the Bazaar.
Even though you didn't have a firstborn son to be killed, you still marked your door.
You still celebrate the Passover.
Okay.
If you have a family, a household, right?
because these are extended families where you've got the first born son who's the son of a first born son who's the son
of a firstborn son. You don't do three lambs. You do one lamb. If you have a small family that
can't eat the whole lamb, you share it with another small family, even if you both have sons.
So you could have one lamb and two sons. There's no reason from the text to believe that God wanted
to kill Israelite children.
Such that it would require a substitute.
The death of the Firstborn is a response to the fact that Pharaoh had murdered the
Israelite boys.
Why would God want to kill more of them?
And have to kill a sheep instead.
The death of the Lamb is not ritualized in any way.
You're not told how to kill the lamb.
So no part of the ritual is based on killing the lamb.
You just have to kill it so you can cook it and eat it.
You're not going to eat it alive.
And so there's no substitution, there's no, nothing.
The day of atonement, the Passover are two different things.
right and
Getting back to the Eucharist, you don't really find much day of atonement stuff in the Eucharist.
Of any kind, right? Is kind of a little sideways thing that we're going to talk about in the
third half. Yeah. To do do diligence, but really it's not there. There are really no elements of
the day of atonement incorporated into the Eucharist.
Yeah, yeah, right.
So there's that.
Yeah.
Okay.
So before we wrap up our second half here, we had another voicemail that we wanted to
play for you.
And this is from Matt.
Hi, fathers.
It's Matt from Ontario, Canada.
I have often heard that the agape meal is an extension of the Eucharist, and even that
these two meals were originally the same event.
Why should we distinguish between the two meals?
Are all meals we share with other Christians and extension of the Eucharist?
And what are the implications of that?
And perhaps most importantly, why is one meal restricted to properly prepare orthodox
Christians and the other not?
You can always tell when someone sends a question they've written it out beforehand,
because that was very concise, good job Matt.
Yeah.
I expect nothing less of a Canadian.
It was a good delivery.
Yeah.
Okay, so he's connecting, you know,
There is this ancient connection to the agape meal, and certainly that resembles more
the Passover meal, right?
Everyone's sitting around a table.
And we're going to finish up talking about eating.
So what's the deal with that?
Why is it kind of separated out?
And why is it that the agape meal is kind of open to even people who might not be able
to receive communion.
What's going on there?
Right.
So part of this is how we've become disassociated from the way sacrifice worked.
Because it's not just that sacrifices were meals, right?
But so if we're talking about a pagan context, right?
Hagen, Greek and Roman temples, for example, had huge banquet halls.
Yeah.
Right. And in their remains, we found bones and remains of all kinds of things, things
that weren't being sacrificed on their altar.
Yes, side dishes. Right. Yeah. Like seerchin and stuff in Corinth, for example. But so we
found all that. So there's even a word for it. It's Trapade Zamada. Yes. Table things.
That's everything sounds cooler when you say it in Greek.
table things. So if we're talking about ancient Israel, right, you'd go, you'd bring the
sacrifice. The sacrifice would be taken from you. The priests would do their thing, right,
to offer it. And then you'd be given your portion back of the meat to eat with your family.
you take that home and you'd eat it, you'd eat it in the context of a meal. Right?
you wouldn't sit in like just eat that.
Yeah, right.
You would have it in the context of a meal.
And so, again, this is not, this is deeply built into the understanding of the Eucharist
as a sacrifice, right?
So, in the very earliest phase of Christianity, while it is still a Judaism essentially, right?
It is one group within second temple Judaism.
Christians were going to the synagogue.
on the Sabbath and then gathering separately as Christians on the Lord's day.
And within that concept of gathering on the Lord's day, they were offering the
Eucharist and then enjoying it in the context of this meal.
And so in the same way that you could have people who are not Christians who are
there eating the meal but not the Eucharist.
Right?
St. Paul has to tell the people in Corinth. Hey don't go eating it
an idol's temple. Yeah.
I'm afraid it's still communion with idols.
Because it's still communion with idols.
And notice, he say, say Paul has to not just say don't eat meat offered to idols.
He has to say don't be eating in an idol's temple.
Yeah. Also. Right. Because you could have the person who says, hey, I'm not eating any
of this stuff that was sacrificed. I'm just going there because it's my trade guild
Whether it's...
Yeah, I like the side dishes.
Right.
Whomever.
And I'm just sort of hanging out there, you know, having a couple
drinks nibbling on some apps, you know, I'm not eating the
sacrifice, right?
I'm not participating in the sacrifice.
I'm not eating the sacrifice, right?
And say Paul says, uh, uh, no, get all the way out, right?
Like, right.
And so that's that's why there's the difference, right?
This was the garbage.
meal was just the sacrificial meal that accompanied the Eucharist.
Yeah.
And so it fit in very well with everybody's understanding of how sacrifice worked.
And in terms of the question of is every meal Christians eat together extension of the Eucharist,
I'll do you one better your whole life should be an extension of the Eucharist
But we'll talk more about that later on.
Yeah, exactly.
So, yeah.
And so, Passover, right, is the shared meal.
Yeah.
And it's focused on eating.
Yeah, so I mean, one question that might come up then,
that some people would have is if a sacrifice is...
eating a meal with your God is God eating the Eucharist? No. No. Yeah, because not all sacrifices are
actually functioned in that way. Right? Like, I mean, am I correct remembering that... Well, the
portion that was burned is the portion to be given to God, but they didn't believe God was actually
eating it yeah there's an offering but not necessarily an eating.
Right, the language it's always used is about the smoke,
right, being a pleasing aroma.
Yeah.
The idea is that God is pleased with the offering.
And so the same would be true of the offering of Christ.
Yeah.
Right.
This is my beloved son in whom I am well pleased.
Yeah.
Not every offering or sacrifice involved giving a specific piece over to God.
And the fact that we don't take a portion of the Eucharist and burn it.
I'm sorry.
is the ritual indication of that.
Right. And the Eucharist is a participation of Christ's sacrifice, which was offered to God.
Yeah. Yeah. So please, exactly.
You don't need to. Again, that would be a kind of repetition of something that's already been done.
Yeah. So yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Alrighty. Well, that's our second half and we're going to take another short break and we'll be right back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Can you believe it will soon be the end of the year?
Now's the time to prepare for 2023 by purchasing calendars and planners for next year.
The ancient Faith Store can help.
You'll find a collection of Orthodox wall calendars and
planners at store.angianfaith.com.
Find and purchase your favorites today
so that you're ready to welcome the new year when it arrives.
Visit store.angianfaith.com and click the calendars tab.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steve
and a Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's it.
558-5-A-F radio.
Welcome back to Lord of Spirits Podcast.
It's the third half of our Thanksgiving episode.
We're talking about the Eucharist.
In the first half, we talked about sacrifice and the priesthood of Jesus Christ.
And second part, we talked about the Passover and how that's related to the Eucharist.
And now we're going to focus in specifically on
on the body and blood of Christ,
what we receive as Holy Communion,
particularly in this part.
So, all right, so where do we begin, Father?
Well, we begin at the beginning.
It is a very good place to start.
It's a very good place to start.
Yes.
Thank you to both Rogers and Hammerstein.
Thank you for that.
some pop culture I knew about.
I have to throw you a bone once in a while.
Thank you.
So we begin with all the way back again, the Old Testament, that with the idea, we talked
about, we've talked about this before on the show back when we talked about the tabernacle
and its furnishings, that one theme in the Torah is that God feeds his people.
Yeah.
Right. He feeds and provides for his people. This is a contrast there, and that's how it's
very directly presented. A contrast with pagan idolatry where once the nostrils are
open on the idol and once the spirit is in the idol, one of the priests' primary jobs
was to feed, dress, care for, dust.
Right?
The idol?
We don't feed God.
Right.
Uh...
And so, yeah, and so that relationship of having to provide for the God is directly reversed.
And one of the places we saw this when we were talking about the tabernacle furnishings
was in the table of the showbred.
The shoebred.
Yeah, which is pronounced showbred, just being spelled.
Probably.
And I recordings of early 17th
entry biblical scholars, I don't know. I'm pretty sure. Probably pretty. Pretty.
So yeah, where there was the table where the loads of bread were kept in the tabernacle,
and then in the temple, which was to the table is God's table, but from that table,
feeding the priests who are serving in the temple.
rather than the priest feeding him.
Yeah.
And then of course, this happens in a very literal sense
in the wilderness, as Israel's in the wilderness,
and is fed with mana and quail.
People forget the quail.
They don't talk about the quail.
How many quail gave their lives in the course of 40 years
in the wilderness?
It's just uncomfortable to think about, you know,
you know, it coming out of the...
noses. Well, that's might be what people are blocking it out. Right? The man we know more
about, right? The sort of flaky bread stuff that fell out of the sky. What is it?
Ma Nga means what is it? Yeah, which made the, I still can't remember where it was that
I lived that had mana donuts, but that just cracked me out. The donuts you look at you say,
What is it?
or they fell out of the sky or I don't know what they were claiming there.
But that's a real place that just looks up in Chino, California.
Oh, well there you go.
Yeah, that's where I saw it.
That's so cool.
Wow.
Man, when I was growing up, when I was finishing growing up, all those someone argued
that I never completed that process.
But the place where I
where I finished high school right around the corner from the school was Jolly Pirate Donuts.
And occasionally during photography class when we were sent out to photograph nature,
we would occasionally photograph Apple Fritters and Krullers as they appeared in nature.
Wow. There you go. That's our donuts. So there's a place called Jolly Pirate Donuts. They did not sell
wine or other strong drink. I would be disappointed. I do not recall that they did.
did.
No, Jolly pirates. I know I'm fine or other. Yeah, very disappointing in the piracy department. Yes.
I mean, that was the whole point of the
Pirate versus Ninja debate, right? Would you rather be a pirate or a ninja?
Right? The pirates, you know, far less competent, far less lethal, but have a much better time.
Yes, absolutely.
Right. Yes.
Yes.
So also more scurvy, but that's a side issue.
Well.
You just need to be Greek pirates and then you're with lemon
Think I'd make a Mr. Pano's joke when we start reading today, but there we go very on top
Well, you're going to a Greek city Indianapolis. That's true. Indiana police. Yes, exactly in the honor of
Anna again
We've now alienated all the Greek listeners.
You can be left listening by the end of this.
I'm actually going to a town called Noblesville and I'm working, trying to work out on my head
with that would be in Greek.
You know, Adi Deepboleys, I don't know, but anyway, that's my from the hip version of the
name of this.
So we've now, we've now all of the Protestant listeners, all of the Roman Catholic listeners
and now all of the Greek listeners have left.
All this left are some scurvy pagans.
Yes.
Um.
So it will fed them by the end of this too, I'm sure.
Yeah.
Um.
So where were we?
Man, a quiz.
This theme of God feeding as people gets picked up
in one of the relatively rare events
featured in all four gospels.
So whatever the birth of Christ,
not in all four gospels.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So other than, right, you have Christ's death and resurrection,
you have His baptism that are in all four.
But relatively rare, right?
So there's no exorcisms in St. John's Gospel, for example.
But the feeding of the 5,000, right?
The feeding of the multitudes is in all four.
Right.
And it's in St. Luke's Gospel sort of twice,
but we won't go into that now.
Um, so, uh,
this event in which Christ feeds multitudes of people. And where that story
occurs in St. John's Gospel is at the beginning of chapter 6. And then later
in chapter 6 there is sort of an extended theological meditation on it as one
Bye.
expect from Saint John the Theologian.
Right.
Which sort of directly connects this idea of God feeding
as people, as expressed in this particular event,
to the Eucharist.
Yeah.
So it's kind of long, but I'm going to read a lot of not all,
but a lot of verses 22 through 59.
And we'll just sort of start off.
will be the occasional ellipsis.
Yes.
I mean, lip sees, yeah.
You'll know it is time to turn the page when you hear the chimering.
Woo-hoo!
When I was in middle school, since we were going to digress again, when I was in middle school,
and we still watched those film strips, remember those everybody, where, you know, they would
play the cassette tape, and then you would hear, you would hear, boom!
I, you know, as a 12-year-old, I worked hard to be able to replicate that sound.
And I was able to be
so successful that I got and because that sound was to indicate that to the teacher to turn to the next
frame in the film strip. I actually got the teacher to start skipping ahead by making that sound. I was so proud of myself.
So there you go. I don't think I've revealed that.
90% of our listeners are way too young to know at all what you're talking about.
No.
We're old men, we're yelling at clouds.
We're pushing 50 pretty hard so okay well all right yes there will be
some ellipses, there will be no bongs.
You know, and by that I mean the sound.
Wow.
This is what happens when we pre-recorded.
We're not super-boss.
So sorry.
That's what this is right here.
Trudy comes, say I'm a snow, there's no trudy.
OK, so right, I'm going to read this.
We will come and write off this.
Yeah, and we're going to kind of stop and start along the way
to offer some comments.
OK, so all right.
Starting with verse 22 of John chapter 6.
On the next day, and that means after the feeding of 5,000, on the next day, the crowd
that remained on the other side of the sea saw that there had been only one boat there,
and that Jesus had not entered the boat with His disciples, but that His disciples had
gone away alone.
Other boats from Tiberius came near the place where they had eaten the bread after the
Lord had given thanks.
So when the crowds saw that Jesus was not there nor His disciples, they themselves got
the boats and went to Capernum seeking Jesus.
When they found him on the other side of the sea, they said to him,
Rabbi, when did you come here?
Jesus answered them, truly, truly, I say to you, you are seeking me,
not because you saw signs, but because you ate your fill of the loaves.
Do not work for the food that perishes, but for the food that endures to eternal life,
which the Son of Man will give to you.
For on him, God the Father has set his seal.
Okay, pause it. Yeah.
So, now that might, what you read there for those following along at home, this is in first 26.
What you said there about, what you read, not because you saw signs, but because you ate your fill of the loaves.
Hmm. Right. That might be confusing to some folks because they might say, wasn't the sign that he fed all those?
people. Right. Right. And all those people were able to eat their field that kind of was the sign,
wasn't it? And so this relates to Saint John uses the term sign in a very particular way
all through his gospel. Yeah. And isn't it sometimes called the book of the seven signs?
like there's seven great science.
Well, so there was another thing.
There was this whole critical theory that St. John's Gospel was a reworking of what they called the
Signs Gospel. I see. Okay. Okay. I'm not going there. I've just heard that. Right. Okay. Right. So,
didn't want to derail you. I'll just go ahead and refer to this. Okay. I was trying to decide
rather to just openly reference this. So...
The now unfortunately departed Dr. Daniel Fletcher,
his doctoral dissertation was about this,
was about St. John's use of signs,
and he particularly connected it to the book of numbers.
And the way signs are used in the book of numbers
in the wilderness.
And so the idea here of a sign is not just Olamir.
circle. But it is a miraculous occurrence which represents the reality of the impending
coming of the kingdom of God. So what Christ is saying here is that you didn't follow
after Jesus.
because they understood what he had done.
Right.
That they looked at what he had done and said,
this is God feeding his people.
This is like the man in the wilderness.
This is, and so this is a sign, right,
that the kingdom of God is near,
that this is the Messiah.
We need to go find him and follow him, right?
They were just looking for him because they were hungry again.
Yeah.
Let's get some food.
Right? They were approaching him. And so this is why he says to them, right, you need
to not be so concerned, striving after filling your belly, right? And be more concerned
about the food that that endures to eternal life, which the son of man, this messianic
title, right, will give you. Right? So that's what he's aiming at. He's saying you guys are
just you
you're in it, you're looking at this like cool magic tricks, right? Yeah.
You have something you want me to do for you right here and now you're not understanding
what's really going on and you're not really trying to come and become my disciples. Gotcha.
All right, we're ready to keep rolling here. Yeah. Okay, verse 28, then they said to him,
what must we do to be doing the works of God? Jesus entered them. This is the work of God that you
to be faithful to him whom he has said.
So they said to him,
then what sign do you do that we may see and trust you?
What work do you perform?
Our fathers ate the man on the wilderness as it is written,
he gave them bread from heaven to eat.
Jesus then said to them,
truly, truly, I say to you,
it was not Moses who gave you the bread from heaven,
but my father gives you the true bread from heaven.
For the bread of God is he who comes down from heaven
and gives life to the world.
It's a posit.
No.
Right? So they're sort of getting closer to the right track, but so they pick up on the
word sign and use it differently.
Right? So they say to him, oh, okay. So you want us to come and follow you and recover
yourself. So you know, I'll show us something.
Yeah. Right. It makes you either the guy that they basically ask for bread again.
Yeah
like our father's eight man in the wilderness, right?
He gave the referendity, so I gave him a more bread, right?
Back to give us some more bread.
And so Jesus's response has these two things.
First of all, it wasn't Moses, right?
It was God, right?
Who gave the bread?
Yeah.
So again, encouraging them to see, right?
So they're saying, what sign will you do?
Yeah.
What will you do?
Like what?
This is what Moses did.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They both look mostly you do.
And he said, it wasn't Moses, right?
It was God.
Meaning if I give you bread from God, this is sign in the other sense, right?
He's trying to push them to a bigger, right?
Not just like I'm a prophet, you should listen to what I say, right?
that Christ is...
beyond that. Right? And so he then he goes to further define the bread he was talking about.
Right? Because he mentioned that bread that continues to eternal life. Right? Now he says that bread is
right, he who comes down from heaven that gives life to the world. Yeah. Okay. So then verse 34,
they said to him, sir, give us this bread always. Jesus said to them, I am the bread of life.
Whoever comes to me shall not hunger and whoever is faithful to me shall never thirst.
But I said to you that you have seen me and yet are not faithful.
Right. So they already have it. Yeah. Yeah. They've met him. Yeah. I gave you got the bread. I'm standing for you.
So okay, skipping ahead a few verses now to verse 41.
So the Jews grumbled about him because he said I am the bread that came down from heaven.
They said...
He said, is not this Jesus the Son of Joseph, whose father and mother we know, how does he
now say, I have come down from heaven?
Jesus answered them, do not grumble among yourselves.
No one can come to me unless the Father who sent me draws him, and I will raise him up
on the last day.
It is written in the prophets, and they will all be taught by God.
Everyone who has heard and learned from the Father comes to me.
that anyone has seen the Father except He who is from God, He has seen the
the Father. Truly, truly I say to you, whoever is faithful to me has eternal life. I am
the bread of life. Your fathers ate the manna and the wilderness, and they died. This
is the bread that comes down from heaven, so that one may eat of it and not die. I am
the living bread that came down from heaven. If anyone eats of this bread, he will live
forever, and the bread that I will give for the life of the world is my flesh.
Okay, pause it there.
So there's a little bit of wordplay going on here with this grumbling.
So the Giants grumble, he says, don't grumble. That word for grumbling is the word that's used
in the Septoe agent for what the Israelites were doing in the wilderness
when they became disaffected. They would grumble. They grumble against Moses. They grumble
against God, right?
Brought us out in the wilderness to die, right?
You know?
right over and over and over again, right?
And so this is deliberately setting up like, well,
not a lot has changed, right? But also that the people who are who are talking to Christ now are still not seeing what
what is really going on in front of them, right? In the same way that those in the wilderness, right?
sort of concert day to day. Oh, we don't have enough water.
we don't have enough food. You know what we do? Right. Like not seeing, hey, remember the
Exodus that just like happened? Right. God brought us up out of Egypt and he's gonna
abandon us in the wilderness. Right. And being faithful to God and trusting him to bring
them through now to the land of Canaan. Right. The same thing is going on in terms of
Jesus, right? They keep giving us some more bread. Right?
But they're still thinking about it, right?
It is a matter of understanding what's really happening, right?
And so even the generation that wasn't like struck down in the wilderness for their grumbling,
right, against God and against Moses, right?
They all died in the wilderness.
But even those who of the next generation that actually went into the land were brought into the land.
They still eventually died.
Right.
Yep.
And so what Christ is talking about is a faithfulness to him and a feeding on the
bread which he is, which he identifies here as his flesh, that he will give for the
life of the world that leads to eternal life, right? Not just to...
another few days of life on this earth.
Yeah, and you get the sense, especially when he says,
the bread I would give for the life of the world is my flesh,
that that sounds nuts to them by what they say next.
Yes.
Okay, verse 52, the Jews say that it sounds nuts.
The Jews then disputed among themselves saying,
how can this man give us this flesh to eat?
So Jesus said to them, truly, truly, I say to you.
you unless you eat the flesh of the Son of Man and drink his blood, you have no life in
you. Whoever feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood has eternal life and I will raise
him up on the last day. For my flesh is true food and my blood is true
drink. Whoever feeds on my flesh and drinks my blood abides in me and I and him. As the
And the living Father sent me and I live because of the Father.
So whoever feeds on me, he...
He also will live because of me.
This is the bread that came down from heaven, not the bread, like the father's eight and
died.
Whoever feeds on this bread will live forever.
Jesus said these things in the synagogue as he taught at Capernaum.
No.
And that last verse is important because we didn't get the setting at the beginning.
We're still there looking for Jesus and found Him in Kepurnaam.
Yeah. But he's actually saying all these things in the synagogue as he's teaching in the synagogue. Yeah.
Right. Which it's kind of seemed especially weird to the law.
What this is what we came here for today. Yeah.
Right. So we talked a little bit about the comparison and contrast that goes on here with the
the manor, right? The bread from heaven.
in the Old Testament. There's also a little bit of a connection to what's going on with the showbred.
In that
Christ here connects
coming to no God
and
and learning from God
this relational element with the eating of the bread.
Right in the same way in which the showbred was eaten in the presence of God.
Right, so there's this connection between...
and drawing close to God that's also sort of inner woven, right, in there.
And some of the verses we skipped developed that a little more, but I mean, it was long enough.
Right. Sure.
But so again, we're not intending to pick on whatever Protestant listeners may still be listening.
Um, but...
This passage we just read, right?
And again, I think this really stems from some of the same kind of reactionary thinking
against medieval Roman Catholicism, which speaks very clearly about eating Christ's flesh
and drinking His blood.
There have been a lot of historical efforts from some quarters to try to argue that this
has nothing to do with the Eucharist.
Yeah
Right. And those arguments are kind of weird and not very good. So one of these arguments
is kind of really circular.
And sort of the denumau of this argument
was made by Rudolf Boltmann.
It was, it was a 20th century German, so at least I'm branching out in who I pick on.
He was kind of the boogie man in a scripture classes when I was in seminary.
He wasn't all bad.
I wouldn't just mostly.
Mostly bad.
All bad, there's only one thing you can do.
He had a lot of quotes that are super ironic now.
Right, like who could believe in the resurrection of
the dead in the age of radio. Wow. Wow. We're in the age of the wireless people. How can we possibly
believe in this primitive superstition? It's current year. It's amazing.
The little scholar making the current year argument. Yes. That's great.
So but what this is based on, again.
The Boltzmann's exhibit A, but this is found more widely than it should be.
People have noticed about St. John's Gospel that sort of the traditional places you'd
go to look for things about the sacraments in the other Gospels aren't there in St. John's
Gospel.
What do I mean by that?
for example
There's this weird little thing in the way Christ baptism, Christ baptism is in St. John's Gospel,
but the way it's narrated, there's this weird thing where it doesn't actually describe the baptism.
Yeah, right. He goes that he interacts with St. John the Forerunner and then it talks about him coming
up out of the water. Yeah, so St. John is avoiding sacraments. Like it skips right. And even more sort of
of Major is St. John's Gospel doesn't have the institution of the Eucharist in it.
When you get to the place of the mystical supper in St. John's Gospel, it describes him washing the disciples' feet, Christ washing the disciples' feet, and doesn't describe him instituting the Eucharist.
Yeah, that's in the other three Gospels.
And so with Boltman and some of the other people who make this argument, it is in part
a relic of this older, now very outdated view that the gospel
especially St. John's Gospel was sort of this weird independent composition that had nothing to do with the other ones and that it was that they were produced by these different communities.
Right. This is the community's right books theory. Yeah. Which tells me that these people have never been a member of a committee.
But yeah.
community sometimes can translate books
but no they don't individual people do
the translator yet and committees argue about it. Right. Right. Right. And hold up the process. Right.
Um, so the uh, but so there's this idea that oh, whatever we see, we have to isolate St. John's
gospel and then whatever we see in it, whatever features we want to notice, that then reflects the
community that produced it. And so the Johanine community, well clearly since it's
There's not the institution of the Eucharist there, and baptism is against Gip.
This is a community that didn't have sacraments.
Or St. John himself, if we have this writer, who, of course, most of the people who hold
this theory, went hold was the actual St. John, but I digress.
The author or authors of St. John's Gospel, or anti-sacramental, or didn't believe in sacraments.
So once you then make
that argument and you come to say, Christ telling St. Nicodemus that he had to be
born of water and the spirit. That can't be referring to baptism. Right. Because you've got this
a priori commitment because St. John is anti-baptism. He's anti-sacrament. And so when Christ and John
6 talks about eating his body, eating his flesh and drinking his blood, he can't be talking about
the Eucharist because St. John and his community didn't have
the Eucharist. They didn't do sacrament. This is why I say this is like a textbook circular argument.
Right, of assuming what you want to prove. Right, right, right, exactly.
You take half the data, argue for a conclusion based on that half the data, and then use that
conclusion to exclude the other half of the data. Right. Don't try this at home, kids.
Yeah, or anywhere really.
Yes, definitely not in school.
This is cool.
This is a waste of time.
This is a sophistry.
Right?
So, right, that dog don't hunt.
You sometimes also get, well, well, look, you know, we're going to accept that St. John
is actually St. John or just that St. John's community was an actually existing church that
we have evidence of, right, that had the Eucharist.
But Christ doesn't institute the Eucharist until right before his death, whereas John 6 takes
place like way before that. So how can Christ be talking about the Eucharist? Because he
hasn't instituted it yet.
Are they trying to say he hasn't thought it up? Hasn't come up with that yet?
And he's like, oh, I'm not sure.
I'm not usually they don't say that.
Usually they say.
something like no one would have understood what he was talking about. And it's like, what?
Christ talked about things during his ministry and no one understood who he was talking about until
after the resurrection, you don't think. Right. Yeah. Like the gospels literally say over and over
again that Christ said things all the time. Right. During his earthly ministry that no one understood
until after the resurrection. Right. Right. There's so this would be par for the course. Depth charges.
Right as
as right to do. And especially in this case, we're literally told in John 6th in the text itself
that no one understood what he was talking about. Yeah. After we left off, the disciples come to Jesus
and say basically like, this is a hard saying. Like, what are you talking about? Right? Yeah. He's
like, and Jesus says, yeah, will you now also leave? Right? Like, yeah, yeah, it's really notable,
I think that he doesn't at any point in this say.
Okay, wait, sorry, guys, guys, you misunderstood.
This is a metaphor for something else.
So calm down, I'm not talking about eating flesh
or drinking blood.
I mean, I'm talking about eating flesh, quote unquote,
and drinking blood, quote unquote.
Right, right.
And if, right?
So let's suppose for the sake of argument
that the Eucharist is quote unquote,
Just symbolic.
That show just broke another pencil.
Right.
Let's say it's just, right, this is just some nebulous, woo-woo sense that it's the body
in blood of Christ, right?
It represents it in some way or something, but isn't, right?
Why would this be the metaphor you choose?
A cannibalism metaphor, apparently.
If there's no reality to it.
It's like cannibalism, guys.
Oh!
You can...
If you could choose any metaphor, right? You could choose any metaphor of the world because the metaphor has no connection to the reality
It's purely a metaphor. Why would you choose this one? Yeah
I mean, this is you know even among pagans
cannibalism was considered to be super oogie you know only certain pagans even did this kind of thing
right yeah
well, and we know that from
later Roman sources.
They get together and eat the body and drink the blood of this crustace.
They're like, these Christians are like cannibals.
What's for us?
They get accused of cannibalism.
Why would you keep using this metaphor?
If it's just a metaphor.
Yeah.
Kind of a fortunate choice.
In this world, you'll have permunutical trouble.
Yes.
So in, in, right, and that creates the biggest problem with trying to take this text in some
other direction is referring to something else, right, is whatever kind of spiritual thing
you want to say it's actually talking about, it's always going to beg the question, so why
this metaphor then?
Yeah, right.
So then why is it compared to this of all things?
Yeah, right. And so, right, bluntly we got to say, right, maybe our doctorate should
come from the Bible, right? Instead of going to the Bible and telling it what it can
and can't say.
None of those traditions of men. Like, it's kind of clear out the face of it what it says,
Right and to me.
most decisive about this. Right? And we talked about this in our how to and not to read the Bible,
right? You can't get into the brain of the original author, right? From from this vantage point,
right? You can try all you like to figure out what was in St. John's head when he wrote this,
right? Good luck to you. You're probably just going to project yourself back into history.
But we can
try to recreate the ear. Who are the first people who heard these words? Right? Probably
read to them. Who are the first people who heard this from St. John? And the first people who
heard this from St. John were a group of people who gathered at least once a week to celebrate
the Eucharist and heard
Right? Someone in the leadership position, depending on where they were, say,
This is my body broken for you. This is my blood shed for you, right?
It participated in the Eucharist.
So the people who originally heard this would have immediately connected it to the Eucharist. Yeah
That they were celebrating at least weekly. Yeah, I mean every indication about what early Christian worship
looks like it says that that's what they're doing.
Yes, and so since that's what they're doing, right?
Since at least 1 Corinthians was written, which was written before St. John's gospel,
they would have immediately jumped to that conclusion.
And there is nothing in the text to dissuade you from that conclusion.
Yeah.
St. John famously has these editorial comments all through his gospel.
Yes, right?
Like he said this to refer to the temple that was his body, where he clarifies
things just
in case there's someone clueless he does not clarify this yeah right at all right it's
allowed to just be what it is right and that's how everyone would have read it and heard it
but so moving on one important element here right more important than just defending the
traditional normal read of it.
actually is that this gives us another little piece in terms of the Eucharist because what Christ says here
talks about
What we could call a positive element of the sacrifice of the Eucharist. Okay, what do I mean by positive?
What we talked about right the forgiveness of sins
Peace with God element we talked about
the offering of thanks, right and praise to to God element
But also that this is positive in the sense of the life of the participants and being positively transformative.
Yeah, I mean, I suggest the remission of sins.
There's what twice in this passage where Christ says, I'm going to raise him up at the last day.
Right.
Yeah, there's a rational promise.
And it is the one who learns from God, the one who knows God, right?
This knowledge is drawn closer to God, right?
encountering him being empowered by him, receiving...
eternal life, right, life and strength, right,
becoming like God, right, through,
through participating in the Eucharist.
You have life in you, yeah.
Right, yeah.
And so that is a critically important element.
Yeah, right.
Right, and connects with the general sacrificial understanding
that you become
like what you worship, or, you know, as we would say,
you are what you eat.
Yes.
So I am a big Mac, anyway.
Right, so that's that positive.
And that's a big part of what it means,
you know, what do we talk about the, in return,
we receive the body and blood of Christ.
Yeah.
So another importance, though, an important image
related to the Eucharist in the
New Testament and importance of this idea of Christ's flesh is related to the image
of the wedding feast.
Yeah, the marriage supper of the Lamb, right?
The wedding celebration.
And this is obviously this originates in the Old Testament in the prophets where God
presents himself as sort of the...
husband of Israel, sometimes separately of Judah and Israel.
Right.
Ritlargen Josea especially.
Yeah, yeah.
And Israel is the unfaithful spouse in this situation, the unfaithful wife.
Right?
And so we see that those themes get continued into the New Testament,
particularly prominent in various ways.
In the parables that Christ tells, many which involve the coming of the bridegroom,
the preparation for a marriage feast, you get these explicit parables that revolve around
wedding feast and marriage feast in Matthew chapter 22 and Luke chapter 12 and Luke chapter 14.
We won't read those whole things here because we're just talking about sort of the theme.
You see this theme of the the wedding supper of the the lamb in
Revelation 19, right? And so this is the way in which
Christ's glorious appearing is discussed. One of the pre-eminent ways is as this marriage celebration.
Right? This sort of conservation of the marriage between Christ and his bride,
right, the church, the assembly, the assembled people of God.
And this is not
to reiterate some things we said last time.
It is not that God got a divorce from Israel
and now has a new wife.
That's not how any of this works.
Yeah.
This is the restoration of that marriage.
So the new covenant is like a renewal of vows, is it worth?
Um, but so
One of the places where this comes out specifically in terms of the Eucharist.
I mean the fact that it's a wedding feast, right?
We can see the obvious sort of connections there, right?
But to put a finer point on it, right?
In John 19 and specifically verses 31 through 37.
So when St. John in particular narrates
Christ's crucifixion and death.
He starts drawing on all of this language from Genesis.
And so the Christ completing his work
and then resting on the Sabbath,
we've talked about some of these things before,
how the Theotokos is referred to as woman repeatedly
and repeatedly in St. John's Gospel and then
gets referred to as mother at the side of the cross and the way
Shah becomes Eve.
Right.
So he's drawing on all of this imagery.
And one of those that I think we pass by or quickly
is in that section of John 19, it
describes the opening of Christ's side.
Alright, wait.
and Christ is pierced with the spear.
And the opening of his side is supposed to call us back
to Adam's side.
Right, being opened in Genesis chapter two,
and Adam's side is open to create woman,
to create his bride.
And when he sees her, he says,
This is, but...
bone of my bone and flesh of my flesh.
Right, and we're told because of this,
the two become one flesh.
And so when Christ's sight is open,
blood and water flow out.
And pick your church father and look this passage up.
Right, this is connected to, right,
the water of baptism and blood in the Eucharist.
Right, which sort of create,
as we've talked about many times, his bride the church.
And so part of this imagery of eating Christ's flesh is becoming one flesh with Christ.
That's cool.
This imagery.
But so the blood there
right? Yeah. Come on, we got out of his side. The blood being involved in the
Eucharist. To anyone who's passingly familiar with the Torah, right? The idea of
drinking Christ's blood raises questions. Yes, right. As it should, you know,
given all that cannibalism stuff we were saying earlier. Yeah, so we got,
here's another voicemail that we got and this is from Nathan. Hello, fathers.
My question has to do with the Eucharist in general and in particular.
the consuming of the wine and or the blood of Christ during the ritual. In the
Old Testament the worshippers were prohibited from drinking the blood and that
blood was taken in particular during the day of atonement into the tabernacle and
was used to atone the elements within the tabernacle to remove the
taint. Is it accurate to say that now in the New Testament we are commanded to
drink the blood primarily because
our bodies are now the tabernacle of the Lord of the Holy Spirit.
And that because we still sin,
I'll be it we shouldn't, but we still do.
Once we have had confession and that sin has been absolved,
we then need the blood of the sacrifice, the blood of the Lord
to go into our bodies which is the tabernacle of the Holy Spirit,
the tent of the Holy Spirit in order to cleanse,
to wipe away to expiate.
to smear away that taint and corruption that's left by that sin.
I look forward to hearing your comments.
Thank you.
There you go. Well, is Ion to something there?
I mean, there's certainly in the liturgy there's talk about
washing away sins and all that sort of stuff related to the blood of Christ.
Yes. Yes.
And in fact, I promised in the second half that we would get to the third half.
Um.
So, yeah, starting with why the blood drinking was forbidden.
Yeah, right.
I think we've talked about this a couple of times.
So, you see this sort of descent happen in the early chapters of Genesis, right, where
in paradise, right, the humans are eating fruit, right?
Nothing dies from fruit, right?
Yeah.
Food is the rest of the creation is offering itself to humanity for food.
In a way that's not doing any harm to anything.
Part of the curse when humanity is expelled from paradise is now you're going to have to bring forth food from the earth.
from the Earth.
through the sweat of your brow, right?
So now the creation isn't gonna sort of offer itself to you as food.
You're gonna have to work to bring forth this food by farming, right?
And this kind of growing and harvesting food, you're killing plants, right?
So there's already a bit of a dissent there, right?
Both in the relationship between man and the rest of creation,
And in terms of...
of now it's dying, it's not offering itself,
you're killing it needing it, right?
But it's only after the flood
that humanity has given permission to eat,
meat, to eat animals.
Yeah, right.
And it's in that context of this further descent
where humanity is now gonna be hunting
That's fellow creature.
right that that's where the the blood drinking right because the blood is the
life that's where that limit is placed right because that is the limit to
remind humanity not to become completely predatory yeah right that's where
there's like a shift right where you're killing and feeding on other living.
fit things, but we don't go so far as life directly feeding on life.
Yeah.
Right.
So it's a limit on sort of predation.
Which that limit's not there for pagans there.
Yeah.
They have blood drinking rituals.
Right.
But this is why this applies the blood drinking part, even in Acts 15 that we talked
about last time.
This is why the blood drinking part applies to everybody.
Right.
the page.
should not have been doing that. It's not like eating pork. Right. Right. It's not like
we didn't read it because it wasn't completely on point. But right before the passage in
Deuteronomy we read about the sort of meal on the pilgrimage. There's actually a comment that
the the the commandment that was there was that the Israelites were not to eat an animal that they
they found dead, but they could take it and give it to a foreigner or sell it to a foreigner.
Right, so there's no problem with their meeting the animal that was found dead.
This was just something that was off limits to the Israelites.
But the blood drinking is off limits to everybody.
Why?
Because it's this signifier of man becoming predatory.
Right?
And we talked about werewolves and cannibalisms and all that.
Last year's Halloween episode, right?
That kind of predatory thing.
was not created to be a predator in the world of any kind.
So that said, why then in the Eucharist?
Yeah, right.
How did it become okay?
Right.
And so there's two main pieces here.
The first one is one that's been sort of a theme all through this is that Christ sacrifices one of self offering.
So Christ is offering His flesh and His blood to us.
We are not...
praying upon Christ. Right? Right? So that's sort of that that first element. Right? So it is
more like it paradise creation offering itself to us as food than like murderous cannibalism. Right?
But the other element is exactly what Nathan was talking about.
Right?
That the light...
that is in Christ's blood is eternal life. It's the life of God. Yeah, it's not animal life. Right,
which purifies, right, which is eternal life, which drives out sins, purifies from sin, cleanses from
sin. This is what I mentioned in the second half that there is kind of sideways an element of
atonement in the Eucharist. This is what I was pointing towards. Yeah, right. Was precisely what Nathan
if it was pointing out that...
this element of the purification of sin. Right. And this is when Christ's blood is
talked about in the Scriptures and the Johanian literatures are a particular place where this happens a lot.
It's talked about in terms of his blood purifying,
purging, washing
us from sin.
not his
blood, appeasing, wrath.
The blood god, blood for the blood god.
Yeah.
So yeah, so those are the, those are the,
the sort of elements surrounding that.
And it's not, again, that like, now it's okay for Christians,
because Acts 15 says it's not.
It's still, right, simple to cannibalism.
Obviously it's still simple.
And...
drinking edible, eating a drinking edible blood is still sinful and still has that predatory significance.
But we are not praying upon Christ. Yeah. Christ is offering His blood to us to purify us,
right, from sin and its effects. Yeah. Yeah. So, okay, we got another question that came in
asking about, we actually have a couple of questions about this, but from a couple different
about the presence of Christ in the Eucharist.
Hello, fathers. My name is Grant and I had a question on the topic of Christ's presence
within the Eucharist. Is God's mystical presence something that is relative to the person receiving
the Eucharist or continually present regardless of who partakes in the mysteries? As an added
topic, can God be present in a different church communion? Even that of a low church,
Protestant group, let's say supposing if they
Orthodox Christian has nowhere else to go. Thank you.
All right. Well, I mean, I think the answer to the first one is, from Orthodox practice
is pretty easy, that Christ is present in the Eucharist no matter the disposition of
the person receiving, which is why it can be bad for you.
Or the priest. Yeah. So, or the disposition of the priest.
Yeah, exactly. You know, we're not donatists.
Right, and that's because...
Christ is the actual offer of the actual sacrifice.
Yeah.
Yep.
Talk about the other side, you know.
So the other piece, well since he phrased it as can God be present, yes.
Yeah, I can do whatever he wants.
Yeah.
That's how much.
So yeah, there's not a cant with God, really.
What?
Uh...
Is this what regularly happens?
Right, might be a better question.
So, I mean, the first thing we have to say,
or at least that I have to say,
I won't speak for Father Andrew
because we are, again, two separate people.
Is that I'm not gonna say more about Protestant worship
than those Protestants would say about their own worship.
Right.
That may seem obvious, but it's not always obvious.
So like if you don't believe that ordination is a sacrament as most Protestant groups don't,
then I'm not going to say that your Protestant ordination was a sacrament.
That just seems sort of basic and respectful to me.
And so if someone says that...
Communion or the Lord's Supper or the Eucharist however they name it if they say hey what we're doing here is not a sacrament
I'm not going to say it is
I'm not going to say they're performing a sacrament when they say they're not performing a sacrament
Okay, well what about the ones who say that they are because that that's a thing too well
Yeah, well, this is a smaller group of this case because we're talking about the presence of Christ right right?
It's true
So most the majority of of Protestants in the United States would not say
that the body and blood of Christ are really present in the elements.
Right. It's true. So I'm not going to say that he is in the elements when they do it, right?
Because that just seems respectful to me, right? To not say they're doing something they don't
think they're doing or want to be doing. Yeah, because Kyle, not Kyle, sorry. Grant did mention
even he said even low church Protestants. Well, that's basically people who don't believe.
Don't say you're outteach that Chris
is truly present there. Right. So, and I believe the speak by it was it said grant
M so I'm going to assume that this question is from Grant Morrison the writer of Doom Patrol
animal man and Chaley in the 90s. There can't be any other grant M's out there so. No. No.
If so, you know grant I haven't seen you since San Diego Comic-Con 1998 you never call you never
We're right.
So, you know, so then in the minority, so then we have minority cases, right?
They're specifically asking about Protestant churches, right?
So, you basically, I mean, congregational groups who knows, right?
But you're basically talking about the Lutherans.
Yeah, and maybe some Anglicans.
Right.
Some, some Anglicans, although they don't, half of them don't want to be called Protestants,
Especially the ones who think.
crisis really present in the elements. Yeah, right. That's they'd rather be called Catholics.
So yeah, you're talking about a smaller group. And so, I mean, in that case, right, I have to fall
back to what St. Aaron A.S. said, you know, we know where the Holy Spirit is, we don't know where he
isn't. Yeah. Yeah, I mean, we can't on the one hand, we can't say, yeah, they've definitely got it
because that's not our place to say that, you know.
But I think it's also problematic to say yeah, they definitely don't
Right, right but so
For an orthodox Christian who doesn't have access to an orthodox church
Which was mentioned to the question right there's a whole other set of issues
About worship and that kind of thing
But then come into play no
Right if the question is aimed at well if I'm unable to go to an orthodox church
It's good.
go to a Lutheran church and receive the Eucharist there and really be receiving Christ.
Right? If that's the nature of the question, right? There's a whole other set of issues
beyond just, right? Is it possible that Christ is present in their elements when they...
Right. Yeah.
...perform their mass. Is that good enough? You know, even in different circumstances?
Right. There's a whole other set. Well, and not just that, but ritual, as we've talked
about a number of times on the show, informs and changes.
you and how you view things and so why not offend everybody? If this is like an ELCA,
very liberal Lutheran church that's still doing liturgical high church things, the way
in which actively participating in that worship over a long period of time is going to inform
and shape you is not going to be into the likeness of Christ.
Yeah, and I think that, and I'm going to touch on this in some of my final comments and
few minutes, but I think that if you think
think of if you go there in terms of like, well, I want to receive communion and maybe they
have it.
Then what you've done is you've extracted that from the ritual context that you just described
or trying to, but it turns out that you can't actually do that.
You're there.
You're participating.
You're being formed.
You're being transformed.
Yep.
So, okay, well, we've got another, as I said, we've got another
speak pipe and other voicemail related to this question of Christ's presence in the Eucharist.
Greetings, Father Andrew and Father Stephen from the Philippines. I have a question on the Eucharist.
From my understanding it seems that in orthodoxy the belief is that Jesus is really
and truly present in the elements but there isn't any clear description of how. I was wondering if
If there is any take like Roman Catholics on Transubstantiation
within Orthodoxy if there's any metaphysical approach.
And secondly, what role does it play to ask the questions
of how when it comes to things like the real presence
in the Eucharist?
Thanks, appreciate what you guys do.
Yeah, so this is Kyle and the Philippines.
So now we've got Kyle in Ireland,
whom we hear from fairly regularly,
and Kyle and the Philippines.
So like the world is really bracketed by Kyle's.
Neither of whom is Kyle Bros. Lofsky.
I'm pretty sure that's true.
Yeah, so this is, I mean the short answer is no.
The long answer is no.
Okay.
Wow.
That was a really low-hanging joke, but you went right for it.
It could be amazing.
They were.
So in large part,
this is a place where,
I think from an orthodox perspective,
the West kind of took a wrong turn.
In the sense that when you read the Eastern fathers,
and they talk about the Eucharist,
they talk about what they-
the Eucharist does. Right. Right. What it's for. What it does in our lives. How it relates
to Christ sacrifice itself, offering the kind of things we've been talking about. When
you read very early in the West, there start to be these Eucharistic debates. And those
debates don't focus on what it does or how it relates to Christ's sacrifice.
those debates are about how it works.
Yeah. Right.
One of my favorite examples of this was the red birdus retrameness feud.
It's still hard to believe that everyone knows all about it.
It was all the hot goss in the 11th century.
But red birdus retrameness.
End friends.
Sorry, I feel like this is like a
I don't know, like a feature on the Muppet Show.
And now for Bertis and Richemnes and Friends.
And so Red Bertis had published a thing about the Eucharist in which he argued that the body and blood of Christ in the Eucharist is his physical body.
from his earthly ministry, so it is the crucified body of Jesus.
It is the body and blood which hung on the cross.
Retrameness countered that the Eucharist is actually Christ resurrected body and blood.
And you may say, wait, what?
Right?
And when I mention this debate to Orthodox people, it's fascinating because I can tell they're
trying to figure out which one we believe.
Right.
And they can't offhand because we don't have this kind of discussion.
Yeah, right.
Christ's body is Christ's body, right?
Yeah.
Is this body at this point in time or is this body at this point in time?
But there was a decision in the West that Red Bird is-
was right and retramed this was wrong. Right. So that shows a different shape of thinking
about these things. And there are all kinds of reasons why this happened. Right. It's
not just like, oh, they were all scholastic and there were no scholastics in the east.
There are people in the east with the saints of the east with the surname Scholasticos.
Okay, so that wasn't this their dad's name.
Right.
There are particular reasons why this happened, right?
Cultural things and why these disputes sort of break out and why they had to be decided
and why they're sort of an official statement in the West on all these issues, right?
Whereas, you know, even when the East issues official statements, there's usually a contradictory
statement issued by someone else shortly thereafter, right?
So it's a different culture issue, that kind of thing.
But that said, these kind of debates continue throughout the history of the Western Church
and as with so many things, and there's a long list of these things, you'll have sort
of multiple traditions going on in the West.
And then when you get to the Protestant Reformation, Protestantism lines up on one side and Roman
Catholicism lines up on the other side of these issues, which previously had been sort
of internal debates.
in the Western Church. And the whole issue that Kyle is asking about about Christ's presence
is one of those issues. So if you read in the summa, Thomas Aquinas' discussion of this,
right. He says that he finds among the fathers two different views right.
The two views he found among the fathers was one view that after the bread and wine were
consecrated, they were now the body and blood of Christ, and no trace of bread or wine remained.
That's what comes to be called transubstantiation. That's the position Thomas Aquinas took.
But he says that there's also a position in the fathers, the people who wrote before him.
that the body and blood of Christ became really physically present in the elements, but there was still bread and wine.
The substance of bread and wine still remained.
And this is basically what becomes constanciation, which is basically the view of Lutheranism.
I know Lutherans.
You guys are unique snowflakes. You don't like consumistanciation. I get it. Okay. You don't want to be categorized. You don't have a box
Yeah
And I know there's more nuance to it that that Luther uses the
Hypostatic Union of Christ two natures with bread and wine. That's super problematic
By the way, but we won't go into that here in panic
There's all kinds of nuance and stuff. I get it
But basically Thomas Aquinas testifies
to existing in the West, these two currents of tradition.
One that becomes the Roman Catholic position authoritatively
and one that basically becomes the position of Lutheranism.
Yeah.
Often called, and substantiation.
Yeah, right, right, which they don't like.
But, yep, right.
And so again, you see these, part of this lining up
on either side of it is because of the conflict
of the Protestant Reformation.
Right. And so that's also something that doesn't exist in the history of the East. Right.
And so there's no need to sort of settle those things.
So if you ask, you know, how is, how is this now the body and blood of Christ, we would say really or truly? Right.
Yeah, now there are there are
From the post-reformation era, from the 17th century, there were a couple of local councils.
I have to do due diligence here, right?
There were a couple of local councils of the Church of Constantinople that are not available
in English.
They're fighting so early available in Greek.
So, you've got to track the Greek down if you want to really read them.
You could find stuff written about them in English, but the actual text.
nobody's bothered to translate in full. At least that I've been able to find.
Where, where they condemned the Lutheran view? And by condemned the Lutheran view,
I don't mean condemned concentration. I mean, they went into detail about the whole
hypostatic union model and condemned that. Okay. That news did not get to certain people in the
the Greek Orthodox Church during the pandemic.
that their own church had condemned that view because some of them promoted the condemned view during
the pandemic. You could edit this out if you wanted to. Otherwise, said, hate mail to Father Andrew.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Take this out. Just send it on.
So to which hour to further, their Greek should be at least as good as mine. I'd refer them back to
those councils. But though they condemned the Lutheran view, the term they used in Greek,
to describe what actually happens.
Some people have wanted to translate
as transubstantiation.
Yes, Matisseosis.
Matisseosis.
Yeah.
That's not really transubstantiation, right?
In the sense that that term does not necessarily include
this idea that there is none of the substance
of bread and wine left.
Yeah.
It's hard to nail down is what I'm saying.
My term is vague.
Right, right.
The most you can get out of that term for sure
is that there's a real change.
Sure.
Right, it now is a different thing,
right, which is hard to derive technical details from.
Right.
But I want to acknowledge that,
because that's the closest thing,
but even that, even if you took that to mean
transubstantiation,
that would be the statement of one local church.
Right.
Yep, and wouldn't be sort of binding on all of the orthodox churches, right?
Yep. And I don't think it is really that simple in terms of what it means. So,
where does the rubber meat the road on this? Right? Like,
there are places where this difference in approach actually makes a practical difference.
And I'll give you
one. The concept in the Roman Church of the perpetual adoration of the sacrament.
Yeah, right. Where they take the Eucharist and put it in a monstrance and put it usually
in a little chapel. And people go down, go and bow down in front of it and, you know, worship
it. Right. That is eucristic adoration, not veneration. Yeah. Yeah. Not not.
because context of the mass, but as a separate act.
Right, because based on a series of decisions regarding the nature of the Eucharist,
that is Christ himself.
Yes.
Now.
Period.
For them.
And therefore, it can be worshiped.
Right.
The problem with that from an Orthodox perspective.
The problem with that from the perspective of the Protestant reformers was,
it was a condemnable idolatry.
is one reformed state of the face as.
So they've viewed it as idolatry, right?
That's not the problem from the orthodox perspective,
or at least not the fundamental problem, right?
The fundamental problem from an orthodox perspective
with that is that this is sort of the ultimate outcome
of focusing on what it is rather than what it does.
Because the Eucharist is to be eaten.
Right, it's food.
Right, it is food for the faithful right
It's Christ giving himself to us as food right and so
Looking at it
Probably get up right if that makes sense if your focus is on what it is
Right and having to find what it is right
But it doesn't make sense if you're focused on what it does
because then it's why aren't you eating it?
Yeah, right. That's how we partake of Christ is by eating it not by worshiping it
It's good question. We got some good questions for this episode. I appreciate everybody who who sent those in
Yeah, and that that I'm sure ticked off the last remaining Catholics
It was probably like three people still listening. Yeah, happy Thanksgiving everybody
All three of you
Maybe they were the turkey...
So they've only been vaguely paying attention and we'll get away with it.
Yeah, yeah.
Trip to fan.
Yeah, so, you know, to some final thoughts, right?
So to kind of actually jump off of what we were just talking about there, and also to put
it within the context of things that I've seen within Orthodox churches, Orthodox people
doing some things that are problematic, shall we say.
For instance.
You have the reality of people who come to church shortly before communion is served, received communion and then leave.
Or, you know, sometimes they'll be there for most of it and then leave right after they receive communion.
Or, and I actually was told this by a priest
up in Canada. I'm not gonna mention where I don't want to call anybody out,
but that the parish that he inherited that they had a practice there where
people would commune once a year, usually on Holy Friday or Holy Saturday.
and they would come by the church, they would stop by, they would drive up, and even one person left their car running out on the curb, and they would come in and expect the priest to communion, and then they would just be sort of on their way.
So literally drive by communion, literally.
So, why do people do this?
I mean, obviously, on some level, it makes sense to them.
It seems right to them.
Right?
what something's in their head that says this is the way to go here,
and they thought it through on some level. And I believe that what it comes down to is this
objectification that we were talking about, that holy communion, maybe not being defined by
precise philosophical terms, like transubstantiation or consubstantiation, holy communion is nonetheless
objectified in a kind of tally's manic way.
I went, I got my communion. I've actually heard people say that. I got my communion.
And this is a problem. This is a problem. And I think some of it stems from, well,
a lot of people probably just uncategized almost entirely, but also some bad
catechesis too. And I think some well-meaning bad catechesis that often focuses on the fact that it
it is the body and blood of Christ.
Absolutely is the body and blood of Christ.
Don't get me wrong.
But when that's the maybe,
some cases exclusive thing you focus in on
with regards to what the Eucharist is,
then there is a space within which it can be treated
in this talismanic way.
Well that's the body and blood of Christ.
Oh wow, you know, sure, all kinds of piety flows from that
and that's beautiful and good.
But when...
Getting the body and blood of Christ is the thing you showed up for.
Then that means that the setting in which it's embedded
Doesn't really matter to you. That's why you can just show up right before communion. Well, that's why you can do the drive-by
You know, that's why you can get it and walk out
It's embedded and we've talked in this episode about all the ways it's embedded
Right, but just a sort of...
summarize that a little bit.
It's embedded within a ritual experience, a ritual that we participate in, that is a
ritual meal that brings us together, that binds us together, that binds us to God, that
vivifies us, that shapes us, and that experience of being bound and shaped and all of that
doesn't come simply from the moment that holy communion goes into our mouths.
There's a lot that precedes that and there's stuff that follows it too.
It's embedded, right?
This episode is releasing on American Thanksgiving.
Sorry, Canadians, we didn't maybe do something for you back in the last month, but, you
know, and Americans, we have a ritual that goes with Thanksgiving.
There's a lot of variations on it, but the one element that pretty much is universal
is a big meal with lots of...
stuff and that it's family gathering together.
This is the American tradition about Thanksgiving.
And often then you'll have people maybe saying something
that they're thankful for, et cetera.
But the family gathering around a big meal with a lot
of variety to it is the kind of core ritual, right?
Well, there's an analogy to this.
I mentioned at the beginning, Mitch Baldwin Phillips
said that Thanksgiving was the last holiday,
American holiday that are not but
ruined. But I think there's a ruining happening, which is, and I know people don't mean anything
bad by this, but often they refer to it as, quote, Turkey Day, Turkey Day, which reduces
it down to a single thing that's being eaten at that meal traditionally, Turkey. But if,
if, if that's what Thanksgiving is, is it's just Turkey, then you've lost all of those beautiful
things that metropolitan Phillip recognize.
as good about this American holiday.
I'm not commenting on the way that people celebrate
or don't celebrate American Thanksgiving.
That is up to you and your family,
your father, confesse, or whatever.
But by analogy, to reduce it to turkey day
is much like reducing the divine liturgy
to getting communion, just getting communion.
Right, we have to understand that
the fact that it is Christ's body and blood is embedded within the context of him as the
priest offering it, as the priest offering himself to us, and we participate in that.
Right?
And especially, you know, like one of the things we often like to talk about on this podcast
is the pagan context in which the practices of early Israel are expressed.
you know, they're surrounded by pigons, right? But it's...
It's not just pagans that do this, but there's this shared meal with your God, right?
When you eat a sacrifice, you're communing with your God in various kinds of ways.
And if you understand that that's what's going on in the divine liturgy, and then within
that context, you see that God Himself is the priest, that God Himself is the offering.
the fact, the very true fact that...
that bread and wine become his body and blood,
that becomes, in a sense, the jewel on this crown.
Right? It's at the center of it for sure,
but it's the center of something.
You can't take it out of that something.
It's centered there.
Now, some people might say,
well, we know what about people who can't come to church
and the priest of the Deacon brings that to them.
Okay, but that is an exceptional circumstance
Let's
born out by necessity
because they're ill because they can't do that but even when the priest or the Deacon brings that to them
There are still prayers that go along with that and there is still a connection of a
communal connection that happens during that that visit and
So it's it's necessary right that it happened that way, but that's not the the way that it is is for everyone
and it's just an extension of...
what is the normal normative way, which is that embedding within the divine
liturgy. Right, so I just wanted to offer that especially because there's a lot
of pious feelings that are surround the way that people think of the
Eucharist and and some of them are really good and the fact that we have this
sense of reverence, you know, and and we see how special and how important it is
that's beautiful. But we need to see that it's embedded and not this kind of
of independent talisman.
that we want to go and acquire
without the larger context of the ritual itself
and the whole life, the whole liturgical life,
not just the service of the divine liturgy,
but the whole liturgical life of the Orthodox Christian.
Father Stephen?
So, in response to one of our collars,
of our colors who...
based on his taste and podcasts. I can only assume is brilliant handsome and successful in life.
I mentioned that not only should our meals with our fellow Christians be an extension
of the Eucharist, but our whole life should be an extension of the Eucharist.
And I met a few things by that. On a basic level, our whole life should
consist of that.
Thanksgiving and praise to God. I've said before, or I've asked before, rhetorically, in
homilies and other places, you know, if when you woke up tomorrow, everything you didn't
thank God for today was gone. Would you have much of anything left? We tend to take everything
for granted until it goes away. Right? When we get sick...
We're kind of mad that we got sick.
Might ask God why he let us get sick.
And, you know, we pray that God would heal us from our sickness.
Rarely do we thank God for our health when we're not sick.
Sort of it, you don't know what you've got till it's gone.
So all of us could use a lot more thankfulness in our life.
Not just, you know, when you're a kid and you get put on the spot
around the dinner table.
on Thanksgiving. And as the caller was alluding to, I think the kind of fellowship and unity
and oneness that's enacted by us coming and receiving the Eucharist together ought to translate
to a unity and a oneness and a family relationship and a brother and sisterhood among Christians
outside of the worship service in our community.
in our lives. So in that sense, also our life should be extension of the Eucharist. But I think one of the most important things that we neglect, and it's bad that we neglect it because it's something if you attend an Orthodox liturgy, we say over and over and over again.
And that is that when we gather to participate in
Christ's voluntary self offering.
him voluntarily offering himself to the Father in a sacrificial way. Part of how we participate
in that in the context of the liturgy is that repeatedly we say that we are also offering our
our lives and ourselves and each other, our whole life, to Christ our God.
that we combine sort of our self-offering with His
when we gather to celebrate the Eucharist.
And I say when we neglect that,
I'm not saying that when we say it in liturgy,
I mean, a lot of times I think it may pass by
so we don't even notice that we're doing it.
But I'm not saying that when we do stop and think about it
that we're being insincere at the moment
when we say that in the liturgy.
But if we think about it a little more.
If I'm going to come on Sunday morning or on a feast day to a liturgy and I'm going
to say that I am offering my whole life to Christ, aren't there a whole lot of things
in my life outside that moment that it would at least minimally be awkward if I tried
to offer them as a sacrifice to God.
Would they at the bare minimum not represent me offering God my best?
Could I reasonably offer a lot of the things I watch on the Internet or streaming services
to God as an offering that would be pleasing to him?
What I offer sort of my worst moments of anger, of criticized.
realizing other people of making fun of other people,
of gossiping about other people.
Could I take those moments and say,
oh, God, I'm offering these to you as a sacrifice.
I hope this pleases you.
We're sincere in the moment of offering our whole lives
to God.
But if we look back at our life,
there's a whole lot there that we would not want
to offer up to Him.
In fact, we'd be kind of embarrassed of
want to hide from him as if that was.
possible. And also looking forward beyond that moment where I may be being sincere
in that moment. But when I look into the next week, how many of my plans that I make for
any given week or month or a year or the future? How many of those plans are based on the
idea that I'm offering that time of that plan. I'm offering that to God.
God is a sacrifice.
Now this isn't to say, oh, we all need to become monks, right?
We all need to do nothing but pray.
We all need to.
But I can gather with my family and enjoy, for example, and thanks to you having a meal
with my family, I can offer that to God as a sacrifice.
There's nothing to be embarrassed or ashamed of there.
There's nothing sinful there.
That is a good thing.
Times of fellowship, times of enjoyment, right?
God's creation. Those aren't things
things that are problematic to offer up to God.
Right?
Sin is.
And we know the difference.
We know the difference.
We know when the difference between doing something to gratify myself and my desires and
enjoying the company of other people and enjoying the goodness of God's creation.
We know the difference between those two things.
We're being precious if we try to argue like there isn't one.
to justify behavior that we know is wrong by comparing it somehow to behavior that we know isn't.
And so I think as we think about the Eucharist and we think about our participation
because even if you're not clergy, you're participating in the Eucharist in this sense.
And we think about what it means to really offer ourselves and our whole life to God.
That it goes
beyond just trying to be sincere during that hour and a half or however long it is that
where we're there in church. And start being honest about how being able to say that sincerely
during that hour and a half means we have to make some changes and reorder some things
in our lives. Amen. Well, that is our show for today. Happy Thanksgiving everyone. Thank
Thank you for listening.
This was not a live show.
but normally we're live and we'd love to hear from you.
If you can't get through live or didn't,
you can email us at Lordofspiritsatheantenfate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us a voicemail at speakpipe.com slash Lordofspirits.
And join us for our live broadcast
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
And if you're one of those people enjoying a turkey sandwich,
you know who you are, come to the Thanksgiving Day.
And if you are on Facebook, you can like our page,
join our discussion group, leave reviews, ratings everywhere,
you listen, but most importantly, share the show with a friend
whom you know is going to love it and benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.aggrafate.com,
stroke support, and help make sure we and lots of
other AFR podcasters stay on the air
and that everyone in the Maddox family has stuffing.
This Thursday.
Thank you.
Good night, and God bless you all.